<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dialogue philosophicall. Wherein natures secret closet is opened, and the cause of all motion in nature shewed ovt of matter and forme, tending to mount mans minde from nature to supernaturall and celestial promotion: and how all things exist in the number of three. : Together with the wittie inuention of an artificiall perpetuall motion, presented to the kings most excellent maiestie. / All which are discoursed betweene two speakers, Philadelph, and Theophrast, brought together by Thomas Tymme, professour of diuinitie..</title>
            <author>Tymme, Thomas, d. 1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 227 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00812</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24416</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S95612</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">57402323</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 57402323</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181123</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00812)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181123)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2170:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dialogue philosophicall. Wherein natures secret closet is opened, and the cause of all motion in nature shewed ovt of matter and forme, tending to mount mans minde from nature to supernaturall and celestial promotion: and how all things exist in the number of three. : Together with the wittie inuention of an artificiall perpetuall motion, presented to the kings most excellent maiestie. / All which are discoursed betweene two speakers, Philadelph, and Theophrast, brought together by Thomas Tymme, professour of diuinitie..</title>
                  <author>Tymme, Thomas, d. 1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 72 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.S. for Clement Knight, and are to be s[oul]d at his Shop in Paules Church-yard, at the signe the Holy Lambe.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: torn, stained, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Astronomy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Perpetual motion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:181123:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:181123:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DIALOGVE <hi>Philoſophicall.</hi> WHEREIN NATVRES SECRET CLOSET IS OPENED, AND THE CAVSE OF ALL MOTION IN NATVRE SHEWED OVT OF MATTER AND Forme, tending to mount mans minde from Nature to Supernaturall and Celeſtiall promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And how all things exiſt in the number of three. Together with the wittie inuention of an Artificiall perpetuall motion, preſented to the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All which are diſcourſed betweene two ſpeakers,</hi> Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delph, <hi>and</hi> Theophraſt, <hi>brought together by Thomas Tymme,</hi> Profeſſour of Diuinitie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>SYRACH. 43.32.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>There are hidden greater things then theſe be, and we haue ſeene, but a fewe of his workes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Clement Knight,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his Shop in Paules Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Holy-Lambe, 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:181123:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:181123:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, Sir <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> Lord Chiefe Iuſtice of his Maieſties Court of Common Pleas, <hi>Thomas Tymme</hi> wiſheth all happineſſe in this life, and in the world to come true felicitie in Chriſt Ieſus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S that famous <hi>Zeuxis,</hi> another <hi>Apelles,</hi> intending to limme in her naturall colours the picture of <hi>Iuno,</hi> ſelected fiue of the moſt beautifull Virgins that were in all Agrigent, that from the comely feature of thoſe, in each part, he might portray a compleate and moſt ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able picture: ſo in like manner (right Honourable) I purpoſing to ſet Dame <hi>Nature</hi> vpon the Stage of the world, in each limme well faſhioned, out of Matter and Forme, haue taken her linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from the Art and wiſedome of the more learned ſort of Philoſophers, that in all her parts (ſo well as I could) ſhe might ſtand faire and well compoſed to the common view, of ſuch eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially as can diſcerne and iudge, a property not common to all. For euery plummet is not for euery ſound, nor euery line for all leauels; neither is it poſſible out of euery blocke to make the ſculpture of <hi>Mercurie,</hi> no more then it is poſſible for euery one without a conuenient Bucket, to draw water from the depth of <hi>Iacobs</hi> Well.</p>
            <p>But your Lordſhip being in all humane Science profoundly learned, and of mature Iudgement (as hath appeared by effect) can with <hi>Protogenes,</hi> diſcipher <hi>Apelles</hi> worke, by the draught of one onely line, and can by your ſublimed wiſedome diſcerne the miſterie of Matter and Forme.</p>
            <p>And to the end your Honour may the better feele my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:181123:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>herein, I haue reduced (as it were) innumerable beames to one Sunne, and many Riuers to one Fountaine, abridging large diſcourſes into a conuenient compendium and methode.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing no Pomegranat can be ſo faire, but that ſome one imperfect and rotten kernell may be found therein, I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech your Honour to deale with ſuch occurent faults, as <hi>Lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries</hi> are wont to deale with precious ſtones, who to hide a cracke or flaw, doe ſet the ſame more deepe in gold. So (my right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Lord) let your Noble name and High reputation of learning and ſage prudence, ſhaddow and adorne my imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this Treatiſe. Wherein, albeit you finde not an Eagles neſt, no more then <hi>Theſeus</hi> did (notwithſtanding through faire promiſes he had long looked for it) yet happily your Honour, at the leaſt ſhall finde a Wrenne, and then at the laſt you may ſay you haue a Bird.</p>
            <p>Now fearing leaſt I paeſſe the due limits of proportion, as did the Myndians, who made their gates greater then their Towne, I ceaſe to ſtay your Lordſhip from your Honourable affaires, crauing pardon for this my boldneſſe, and beſeeching God to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe your dayes and yeeres with deſired health, to your ioy and comfort, and to the good of this Church and Common-wealth of great Britaine.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours moſt humble,</hi> Thomas Tymme.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:181123:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Almighty Creatour of the Heauens and the Earth, (Chriſtian Reader) hath ſet before our eyes two moſt principall Bookes: the one of Nature, the other of his written Word. By theſe we know that, God was before all times, infinitely one, comprehending all things that now be, in himſelfe: and being the beginning of Time, created thoſe things in number, meaſure, and waight, adorning his worke moſt wonderfully with theſe three Inſtruments, as with the firſt Formes. And formed thus this vniuerſall frame after the ſimilitude of Vnitie, in circular compaſſe, in pure and meere ſimplicitie.</p>
            <p>The wiſedome of Natures booke, men commonly call <hi>Naturall Philoſophie,</hi> which ſerueth to allure to the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of that great and incomprehenſible God, that wee might glorifie him in the greatneſſe of his worke. For the ruled Motions of the Orbes: the wonderfull workmanſhip of ſo many ſtarrie Tents: the connexion, agreement, force, vertue, and beauty of the Elements: the ſcituation, firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſpreading of the Earth amidſt the waters: and ſo many ſundry natures and creatures in the world, are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie interpreters to teach vs, that God is the efficient cauſe of them, and that he is manifeſted in them, and by them, as their finall cauſe to whom alſo they tend. Yea, the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Motions which belong to all creatures, euen to Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables, caſting their rootes downewards, and their ſprouts vpwards, doe therein ſet forth the power and wiſedome of the omnipotent Creator. But the Mirrour wherein we may
<pb facs="tcp:181123:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>yet better behold God, is Man, a little World, in whom ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and is imprinted a Diuine Eſſence, the like whereof is not to be found in any viſible creature beſides. How ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie is it then, for men to conſider the workes of God in his creatures? And how much more neceſſarie is it to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde their owne perſon and nature, wherein there are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as many meruailous workes of God, as there are in the whole frame beſides? For what will it profit a man to meaſure the Vniuerſall: to compaſſe the whole Elementarie Region: to know the things in them, and their nature: and in the meane time to be ignorant of himſelfe? For albeit, a generall knowledge of all the creatures of this viſible world, will greatly helpe to leade man to the knowledge of God the Creator, yet he ſhall neuer be able to know him well, if with all he know not himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plato</hi> ſearching by the meanes of Motion, what was the ſubſtance, nature, and immortalitie of mans Soule, attained to the vnderſtanding of the Diuine Eſſence. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> alſo taking the ſame way, acknowledgeth that he knew God vnder the name of the firſt Mouer, who is perpetuall and immoueable. But the wiſedome Supernaturall, called <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> reuealed in the written word of God, being farre more excellent then all naturall <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> ſublimeth our ſpirits, through the light of the diuine Spirit, to mount (as it were) by <hi>Iacobs ladder,</hi> with Phoenix wings, from the things of Nature to Celeſtiall and Diuine things, whereby we haue a light and bright vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>If man had not ſinned, the booke of <hi>Nature</hi> would haue ſufficed to haue kept him alwaies in the knowledge &amp; obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of God his Creator. For then he ſhould himſelfe haue carried that Booke whole &amp; perfect, imprinted in his heart and minde, neither ſhould his Soule haue needed any other Teacher to know it ſelfe; but it ſelfe ſhould haue clearely beheld and contemplated it ſelfe ſo long as ſhe preferred and preſerued her firſt light, wherein God had created her. But now that ſhe is in the body as it were ſome excellent
<pb facs="tcp:181123:4"/>picture of <hi>Apelles,</hi> fallen into a ſinke of mire, couered and compaſſed about with thicke miſtes and obſcure darkneſſe, it is very needefull that we ſhould haue another new light brought to vs from Heauen, not naturall, as the firſt, but ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall. For this cauſe God hath giuen vs his ſacred Booke, by meanes whereof, as alſo by his holy ſpirit, hee communicateth to vs as much heauenly light as is needfull for the knowledge of our ſelues, and of his high Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>Now (Chriſtian Reader) becauſe all things liue, moue, and haue their being in God, a fire moſt pure &amp; ſimple, and a light inacceſlible, (from whom that ſubtill fire which pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrateth into euery thing, and is the cauſe of all motion, proceedeth, and hath originall,) I haue compiled this <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue,</hi> diſcourſing naturall Philoſophie, that thereby thou mayeſt not onely pry into Nature, but alſo throughly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the cauſe and beginning thereof to be in God. And for that rare things moue much, I haue thought it pertinent to this Treatiſe, to ſet before thee a moſt ſtrange and wittie inuention of another <hi>Archimedes,</hi> which concerneth Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall perpetuall motion, immitating Nature by a liuely pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of the Inſtrument it ſelfe, as it was preſented to the Kings moſt royall hands, by <hi>Cornelius Drebble</hi> of Alchmar in Holland, and entertained according to the worthineſſe of of ſuch, a gift my paines herein beſtowed and intended for thy profit and pleaſure, if it ſeeme but as Iron, yet let it ſerue for the Forge and Anuile of good conceit, if the diſcourſe ſeeme rough, ſhaddow it I pray thee with the curtaine of ſmooth excuſe: but if it be found of thee as Bullion, fit for the Mint, and currant for the ſtampe, then grace it with the golden approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Touch</hi> and <hi>Teſte.</hi> So ſhall I reſt thine during life,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Tymme.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:181123:5"/>
            <list>
               <head>The Contents of the firſt part of this Treatiſe.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 1.</hi> Sheweth the beginning of all naturall things, and their first Matter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 2.</hi> Sheweth the forme of things naturall, and the preparations thereunto.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 3.</hi> Concerneth Power: which is a preparation of Matter to receiue forme.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 4.</hi> Concerneth Matter, Forme, and Temperament.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 5.</hi> Concerneth the three principles of Nature: <hi>viz. Salt Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercurie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 6.</hi> Concerneth the exiſtence of Man in the number of three.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The Contents of the ſecond part.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 1.</hi> Concerneth the naturall Heauens, and their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 2.</hi> Concerneth the naturall cauſe of the motion of the Sea.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 3.</hi> Concerneth the nature and qualitie of the earth: and the handling of a queſtion whether the Earth hath naturall motion or no.</item>
               <item>Alſo herein is deſcribed an Inſtrument of perpetuall Motion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 4.</hi> Concerneth the cauſe of all naturall cauſes: and the motion of mans ſoule to Celeſtiall promotion.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:181123:5"/>
            <head>NATVRES CLOSET OPENED, BY THE DISCOVRSE OF TWO SPEAKERS, <hi>PHILA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DELPH</hi> AND <hi>THEOPHRAST.</hi> (⁂)</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N very good time I diſcry my old friend <hi>Theophraſt</hi> (if my ſight faile me not,) with whom I haue of long time deſired to conferre about ſome points in naturall Philoſophie, wherein I much deſire to be informed. I will therefore goe meete with him preſently, leaſt he turne ſome other way, and ſo I miſſe of my purpoſe, Well met my good friend <hi>Theophraſt.</hi> Your abſence from this Country in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, hath depriued me of your company a long time: but now you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing happily returned, in very kinde manner I giue you the welcome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I requite your kindneſſe, reioycing in your welfare my deere <hi>Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delph,</hi> wiſhing to thee as much good as to my ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>From your well-wiſhing minde, let me craue of you the ſpending ſometime to acquaint mee with that admirable Queene of the world, Dame <hi>Nature,</hi> whom I ſuppoſe you know, conſidering your great tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes. Tell mee therefore in good fellowſhip, haue you beene in that Ladies Court, and ſeene her moſt rich Treaſurie and Cloſet, repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed (as men write) with ineſtimable iewels?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:181123:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue not deſired to pleaſe my externall ſenſes herein, but to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold her in contemplation, which hath contented me, without too cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious a ſcrutenie, not daring to diue deeper than I had meanes to ſwim.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>What is the beginning of naturall things? and what thing is <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>All things which come forth by their owne accord, and by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward force and vertue, are ſaid to be by nature; as the foure elements of the world, mettals, all kinde of plants, all liuing creatures, and the parts of theſe. So that this ſecret and inward beginning of procreation and off-ſpring, and of all action, is not onely called, but is in very deede the nature of euery thing. To this <hi>Nature</hi> a certaine matter is added: as to the forming of an Image, wood or mettall muſt be put, vpon which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the name of <hi>Nature</hi> muſt neceſſarily be beſtowed. And thus euery thing is made of two natures, which cannot be by any meanes diſioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or conſiſt in any place being ſeperated: and both theſe natures doe ſo affect and like the other, that being knit together they liue, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they die. That matter, which is brought to forme, as the firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, abideth alwaies one and the ſame, vntill the compound matter it ſelfe doth periſh and paſſe into another, for euery ſubſtance which is begotten, is begotten, and hath being of another ſubiect: as ayre is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of water: plants and liuing creatures of ſeede: neither is there any thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, now made of nothing. But yet the ſubiect whereof any thing is made, was made of matter and forme: the <hi>Forme</hi> periſheth and paſſeth away, and another ſucceedeth, and taketh away priuation, but the ſelfe and ſame matter abideth, which matter is ready and apt to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the ſubdued and decayed forme. It is therefore neceſſarie, that ſomething be brought and added after ſuch a manner, that there may be a viceſſitude and conuerſion of things in the remainder, and ſurui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour. Whereby it is to be vnderſtoode, that matter is not begotten from any beginning, and is indiſſoluble and immortall throughout all ages: and that alſo as it was without beginning, ſo alſo it is without deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And when any thing is begotten, onely the forme thereof is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created, and ſheweth it ſelfe, and when it dieth and is extinguiſhed, the ſame forme faileth: but the common matter of all things doe euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine one and the ſame. For if vpon the vaniſhing of any thing, the matter thereof ſhould die and periſh, then the common Maſſe of all things had long ſince come to nothing: neither could mankinde, nor the whole nature of things, nor yet the world it ſelfe, ſtand and continue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe things I well vnderſtand. Now I pray you ſhew me if euery thing that is begotten, proceeded from another, from whence it tooke
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:181123:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>matter, as from a fountaine: which if it be ſo, why then at the laſt doe we deſire the Elements, which doe flow in the procreation of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>They flow to this end, that they may adde and ſupply matter to things begotten and conſtituted. For the matter which proceeded firſt from the elements, paſſed into a certaine ſubiect, from whence ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and ariſeth all that we behold and ſee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I doe not well vnderſtand your meaning, open it therefore if you pleaſe more plainely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>That ſubiect body, out of which by procreation, ſomething is borne and commeth to light, is eyther wholy ſimple or compound: out of a ſimple body nothing can be deriued, but that which is ſimple, becauſe the motion thereof is ſimple and vniforme. For the which cauſe the Elements are reſolued into themſelues onely: and in like manner returne backe againe, and euery one is made of another ſimple. But of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound body no ſimple is made, but another compound, which can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer proceede out of a ſimple.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I take it without further queſtion, that it is as you affirme herein.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Conclude then, that there is one matter of the elements, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for compound bodies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſay that the conſequent neceſſarily followeth, albeit it doth n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> plainely appeare vnto me to my content.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I will therefore deliuer it more plainely. The matter of the Eleme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> is ſimple: but the matter of bodies compounded of the Elements is compounded. In the ſimple Elements are the beginnings onely: in the compound are not onely the firſt beginnings, but alſo the Elements. The commutation of the Elements betweene themſelues is moſt ſimple; wherein that which is firſt, ſupplieth ſimple matter to the latter: but the matter of one Element cannot ſuffice to the begetting of mixed and compound bodies, but the whole foure muſt neceſſarily be mixed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the procreation of bodies compound: for aſſure your ſelfe, that golde, ſiluer, Iron, and all mettals, as alſo the precious ſtone called the Vnion, the Hyacynth, the Smaragde, and all ſorts of gemmes and pearles, tooke their originall not from one Element alone, but from all ſoure in mixture; or rather if you will from the earth, as from their mother; but ſo as ſhe hauing a conuenient temper by the other, was the more fit for the procreating faculty. So alſo plants and liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures come not immediately and of the earth, but by the meanes of ſeed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:181123:7"/>by longer tract of time, and by many changes comming betweene: but yet they haue receiued their matter out of the Elements, which were kept in the ſeede and facultie nutritiue, ſo that this their matter, is not ſimple of the Elements, and without all forme, but being much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, is now called a naturall body, and properly a ſubiect, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the incorrupt ſubſtances of the foure Elements doe abide. Moreouer, if another body ſhould come forth of this dying body, thoſe incorrupt ſubſtances will remaine ſafe and ſound, albeit in another proportion, and in another order of mixture, vntill at the length by extreame deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, euery of them returne into their natures, and be reſtored to their vniuerſalitie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you now define vnto me what thing is matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Matter is a conſtant and permanent ſubiect, out of which all things are procreated: and albeit, it is not found by it ſelfe, and of the remote forme, yet it is firſt put into the body, as the foundation wherein forme is, and vpon which it is ſupported, and is as it were the receptacle of all alterations and changes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>There are certaine Philoſophers, as <hi>Alexander,</hi> and others who haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ught me, that all things in the vniuerſall world, and the very formes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> things, doe ſpring and proceede from the mixture of Elements. Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing, that the whole forme is the ſubſtance of the naturall thing, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>at there is incident to the ſame a certaine harmonie and conſent of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>fections and qualities, which is the forme by which it hath the name, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d is different from the reſt: for euery thing is knowne, and offereth it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>fe to our ſenſe, by theſe his qualities.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I will not ſtand to handle theſe things, which are but trifles: but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>inke it better to ſpend the time vpon more waighty and profitable queſtions, what you hold concerning the formes of Elements I care not, if ſo be you agree with the beſt ſort of Philoſophers, that the formes of compound bodies are placed in the kinde of ſubſtances.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I doe agree with them, yet lately I haue learned of ſome very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for Philoſophie, that the formes of Elements are reckoned among qualities, which queſtion albeit you thinke it a trifle, yet would I gladly heare your opinion therein.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I doe not thinke that any thing can be defined concerning theſe, which is either certaine, conſtant, or approued by generall conſent, ſo long as mans minde is ſhut vp in the priſon of his body, neither can he know by his ſenſes, what Matter, and Forme is: I rather encline to their opinion, which affirme that as the formes of compound bodies, are pure
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:181123:7"/>ſubſtances, ſo alſo the formes of the Elements are pure ſubſtances. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> you giue credit to this opinion, and haue reaſon for it, let me heare it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alexander</hi> ſaith thus: that forme which commeth from Art, is not by any manner of meanes a ſubſtance, no more then Art it ſelfe: but the forme which is of nature, is without doubt a ſubſtance, euen as is <hi>Nature</hi> her ſelfe, for we make heate and drineſſe in fire (which is a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and ſimple body) a forme; and affirme that there is in them and from them, a naturall lightneſſe, for this is the beginning of motion tending vpwards. By which words he plainely affirmeth, that the forme of a naturall compound, is a ſubſtance, and the quality of the Element is as the Artifice of a made matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>But ſhut not the booke as yet, till you haue read further.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Contented. It followeth in this manner: for the which cauſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> forme cannot ſubſiſt, if it be ſeparated and remoued apart from the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet wee make no doubt but they both are ſubſtances. For as the matter, ſo alſo the naturall forme is a ſubſtance: for the parts of a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance are ſubſtances. Now becauſe either part is a ſubſtance, that which conſiſteth of both, is both the ſubſtance, and all one nature, not ſuch as wee ſee in an Artifice. For the ſubiect of theſe is ſubſtance: bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the forme is thought to be a qualitie. Are not theſe words plaine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes truly, they are plaine enough againſt you, to confirme my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, therfore out of them I frame this argument againſt you. The part (ſaith <hi>Alexander</hi>) of a ſubſtance, are ſubſtances: but as well the Element as the body compound is a ſubſtance: therefore as the parts of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound body, ſo alſo the parts of the Element, are ſubſtances, if by this reaſon <hi>Alexander</hi> ſheweth that the forme of a naturall compound is a ſubſtance, he will not denie but that the forme of the ſame Element is to be referred to a kinde of ſubſtance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt confeſſe you haue taken me in my owne ſnare.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell me <hi>Philadelph,</hi> is there not one common matter of all things? Which granted (as I know you will not denie it) you muſt then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that the eſſences of naturall things, doe much differ among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, how then can you make thoſe ſubſtantiall eſſences of things to be differences from matter, which is common to all things? or how ſhall euery thing take and deriue the proper eſſence of his kinde, from that rude and common beginning of all things?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſee not how.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:181123:8"/>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>If there be diuers orders and differences of kindes among things which conſiſt of nature: if euery thing hath his proper nature, there muſt be ſome other thing appointed; beſides that common matter, by which euery particular thing may haue his forme and particular nature.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>This muſt needes be.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophrast.</speaker>
                  <p>But that thing whatſoeuer it be, which giueth eſſence to the whole, muſt needes be ſome excellent thing, and farre more excellent than matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>What elſe? for thereof euery thing hath his name.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>And this is the very ſame which thou art wont to call the forme of a thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Not onely I, but all for the moſt part, are wont ſo to call it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Forme, muſt needes be the firſt and chiefe part of all things.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I make no doubt to affirme the ſame of ſecond bodies, but not ſo of the Elements, of which there is a farre different conſideration: for the ſpecies of theſe is a quality.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>You doe roame as it were in a certaine maze. I ſhewed you before, that after one and the ſame manner, the forme of euery ſimple or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound ſubſtance, is a ſubſtance: but let vs come to euery one particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and vnfold their natures. A plant or mettall is indebted to his forme, that the one is a plant, and that the other is mettall, and ſo of all others it may be ſaid, of what kinde ſo euer they be: Is this true, or no?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>All men ſay ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Then muſt needes the Element take the reaſon of being an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, from forme onely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>This alſo is confeſſed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>But an Element is a ſubſtance by forme, and a ſubſtance of this kind. For that it may be a ſubſtance of this or that kinde, that is, that it may be fire or earth, it hath not ſuch power to take ſuch being from matter, which is common to all things.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>This I granted before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:181123:8"/>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>From whence then hath it ſuch being?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>From forme.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Therefore this forme of the Element, by which fire, is fire, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth from this, is a ſubſtance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>How?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>For, if fire be granted to be a ſubſtance (as you confeſſe it is) that ſame which giueth and cauſeth it to be fire, is alſo a ſubſtance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>It muſt needes follow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſame is the reaſon of fire, which you denie not: whereby it commeth to pafie neceſſarily to be concluded, that both the forme of fire, and alſo of euery other Element is a ſubſtance. Therefore when by definition we will comprehend an Element, or other ſubſtance, we doe not define it with a figure, with colour, with beautie, or turpitude, but with the ſame ſubſtance from whence euery thing naturall hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken his effence, and that is forme, which concludeth the definition of any thing. Moreouer as a plant differeth by varietie and diſſimilitude of forme from mettall, and a liuing creature from a plant: ſo alſo an Element, which alſo is a ſubſtance, differeth from other ſubſtances by a certaine naturall and in-ſet ſubſtance proper vnto it. For as no acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents can accompliſh and perfect the eſſence of a ſubſtance, ſo no more can that eſſentiall difference of things be made of an accident, becauſe it cannot change the eſſence of a naturall thing. Seeing then in all other ſubſtances that which diſſeuereth and diſcerneth one from another, is ſubſtance: how can it be that it ſhould not doe the like in Elements, which are true ſubſtances?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Euery ſubſtance that is comprehended by the eſſences, is compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of ſubſtance and forme, as out of his parts:<note place="margin">The ſimple mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is a matter of the ſimilar bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, compounded of the Elements. The matter of the diſſimilar body is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</note> euen as all ſuch things as Art hath made out of the matter of mettall, ſtone, or wood, haue a certaine forme and ornament from Art. The Element which is a ſimple body, hath for his ſubiect a ſimple matter, wholy without forme, and deſtitute of all faſhion. But a compound, mixt, and naturall body, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not haue a ſimple ſubiect, for we ſee that a body of one ſort or faſhion euery way like vnto it ſelfe, (which the Grecians call <hi>ſimilar</hi>) which of all the compounds is moſt ſimple by many degrees, hath a ſubiect mixed and encreaſed out of the foure Elements, as Golde, Stone, or Iron: for it was granted afore that the matter of a mixed body, is deriued from the foure Elements, which reſeruing their formes, doe abide in a mixed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:181123:9"/>body: for if their formes ſhould vtterly periſh, then ſhould there be in very deed a deſtruction, and no mixture at all. Moreouer, beholding and conſidering a body of many formes, and of a diuers nature, as this Roſe, or that pleaſing Lawrell Tree, I plainely diſcerne by the beholding of the eye, (which is the ſureſt demonſtration) that the ſubiect hath a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die conſiſting of many vnlike parts: as one of the roote, one of the barke, another of the wood, another of the marrow or ſap, another of the leaues, and another of the berries. Furthermore, that there is a greater difference betweene a vegetiue and the ſubiect of a liuiing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, becauſe beſides the diuerſitie of parts, it hath conformation and a manifold figure or ſhape.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>My good friend <hi>Philadelph,</hi> you haue ſpoken truly and profitably of a matter knowne to be true by common ſenſe and experience: whereof if any man demaund a reaſon, beſide ſenſe and experience, if he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the offices and actions of things liuing, he ſhall ſee the ſinewes, the bones, and the fleſh, to haue ſuch different faculties and vſe, that he will affirme their natures and eſſences to be much different. Moreouer, theſe ſimilar parts as they are compounded in themſelues, haue certaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per temperaments, which being kept ſound and pure, it is likely that their natures which are partakers of the ſame temperament doe remaine vncorrupt: for what can diſſolue them their temperament being pure? Thus it is plaine, that in the compoſition of a liuing creature, the bones, the ſinewes, the fleſh, the filmes, and other ſimilar parts doe differ, not onely in colour, thickneſſe, and in other qualities and feature, but alſo in the naturall temperament, proper eſſence, and in forme: if any man thinke, that theſe are not ſufficient to ſet forth the differences of things, by what other reaſon I pray you will he diſtinguiſh their eſſences? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or what bodies can he bethinke him of, whoſe eſſence is more then that of theirs? and yet no man will denie, but that theſe haue their ſubſtance, except he be come to that madneſſe or contentious diſpoſition, that hee dare ſay, that as well the parts of our body, as alſo other bodies which are moſt different, are ſeparated onely in accidents. But let him eſteeme as he pleaſe the decree of the moſt auncient Philoſophers long agoe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded, who reiecting formes, affirmed that all things were made, and are to be diſcerned onely by accidents. Wherefore to come more neere to the ſentence which thou haſt propounded, I auow, that not onely the bodies of liuing creatures, and of plants, but alſo of ſtones, and of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine mettals, haue a manifold ſubiect, whoſe parts doe differ in forme and in eſſence, and not in accidence onely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>There are ſome which affirme, that the forme of the foure begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of <hi>Nature</hi> is moſt ſimple, &amp; that the bodies compounded of them are more perfect, for if you marke well, you ſhall ſee that there is a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter forme in a ſtone, then in the Element thereof, which is earth, and a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:181123:9"/>better in a plant, then in a ſtone: and a much better forme in a liuing creature, then in a plant: as if nature had giuen to euery of theſe, a forme, according to the worthineſſe of the ſubiect. Will you ſay then that theſe things which haue a compounded ſubiect, haue not alſo a compounded forme? Or if you grant that, will you not alſo yeeld, that the forme of euery thing is naturall, and begotten out of thoſe formes, which are in the compoſition of his owne ſubiect? which if you grant to be ſo, you muſt needs alſo confeſſe, that the ſame is not to be taken from any other, neither that it hath any other faculties than ſuch as they giue to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſimples. How thinke you of theſe reaſons? let me heare what you can ſay againſt them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I know the Authors from whence theſe things are drawne by you, which cannot be determined without much contention: That which I haue to ſay herein, ſhall be according to <hi>Aristotles</hi> minde and opinion, namely, that the forme of an Element is a ſimple, in a ſimple ſubiect. And that the forme of a naturall compound body, though the ſubiect be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering and coaugmented out of diuers parts, yet the forme of the whole is ſimple: and ſuch as vſing a manifold and compounded ſubiect, hath manifold and compounded faculties: by which the perfection thereof is to be diſcerned.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>This is to me ſomewhat obſcure, therefore I pray you expreſſe your meaning more plainely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>There are many orders of formes, digeſted out of the ſorts and kindes of offices: for ſeeing forme is a certaine nature, &amp; the ſame the beginning of motion, it muſt be deemed a moſt ſimple and imperfect forme, and of baſeſt degree, which ſhall be the cauſe but of one ſimple motion.<note place="margin">The order of Formes. Forme the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of motion.</note> But the forme which ſhal be the worker of many different motions, ſhal be more perfect than that, and alſo of a more high degree. So the forme of an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which becauſe by the change of the place, is onely caried vpward or downward, is thought moſt imperfect &amp; abiect: the forme of a plant which ſtirreth vp motion of nouriſhment, of encreaſe, &amp; of procreation, is therefore accounted more perfect and more noble than that of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And the forme of a liuing creature is more noble than that of a plant, which beſide the other giueth ſenſe and a voluntary progreſſe. But of all other, the forme of a man is of the higheſt, &amp; moſt perfect degree, which aboue all things, is endued from God with the gift of a Deuine mind. And it is conuenient, that the forme which is the more perfect, and endued with moſt faculties, ſhould haue a more compleat &amp; better furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed body, as a ſhop or workhouſe, that it might the better apply the great ſtore and variety of Inſtruments to diuers and ſundry ſorts of offices, for neither the perfect forme which is able to effect in it ſelfe many formes, ſhal paſſe into a matter that is rude, ſimple, &amp; vnprepared: nor yet if it ſhal paſſe, can it either ſtand therein ſafe &amp; ſound, or fully execute all his offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the ſame. The matter of the Elements is altogether ſimple &amp; rude,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:181123:10"/>as is the ſubiect, which is in mettall or ſtone, compounded of the onely temper of the Elements. To plants is giuen both a ſubiect diſſimilar, and alſo a body organicall: but for ſo much as the oddes or diſſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is more in liuing creatures then in plants, the ſame diſſimilitude is a better &amp; more comely feature: finally, Nature hath ſo excellently formed man, as if ſhe intended (out of him, as out of an examplar or patterne of a moſt abſolute and perfect worke) to cauſe him to be admired and eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med more excellent than all other naturall things. After this manner therefore the forme of all things is ſimple, but the more highly it is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limed and aduanced, and by how much it containeth in it the effecting faculties, by ſo much the more it hath obtained a more abſolute ſubiect, furniſhed and more fit to effect any thing: for the body is made for the formes ſake, and not the forme for the bodies ſake.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Be it as you ſay: yet they proceede further, and affirme, that if the formes of ſimples (out of which, things are compounded) are preſerued whole in the compound, and periſh not, it is then conuenient that they ſhould be mingled and compounded among themſelues, as are the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters wherein they are ſeated, and that out of ſuch mixture the forme of the whole ſhould ſpring: and that the ſame is a certaine harmony, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded as it were of well tuned and fitted formes: for the action of a plant, or of a whole liuing creature, proceedeth from the functions and faculties of all the parts, conſpiring or agreeing together in one: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the action of the whole any other then the action of all the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing parts. Thus (ſay they) Nature maketh it plaine, that nothing is to be beleeued to be the forme of the whole, but that which is a iuſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the ſingular formes, and an agreement ariſing no where elſe, but out of them. Therefore <hi>Alexander</hi> ſaith, ſimple bodies whoſe ſubiect is ſimple, haue gotten a ſimple forme and nature. But in thoſe bodies wherein there is not a ſimple ſubiect, but a body already or a compound; in the ſame, the forme is more perfect, by the gallantneſſe, and braue fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thereof. And not without cauſe; for that forme which is in the matter, &amp; in the ſubiect bringeth ſomewhat to the forme of thoſe which are compound. And ſoone after he ſaith: the multitude of formes and their mixture (which is diuers) in ſubiect bodies, may bring an equall cauſe of change. This opinion is ſo contrarie to that which you before haue affirmed, that I for my part know not what to hold.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Againſt your <hi>Alexander</hi> I oppoſe that worthy Philoſopher <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who diſputing about this poſition, determined, that neither the ſoule nor forme was a harmony. For harmony is a proportion of well tuned and conſenting voyces. But this proportion is not a ſubſtance: but the ſoule is a ſubſtance: moreouer, the ſoule is before the body, and farre more excellent, being the Queene of the ſame, moderating and mouing it. But the Harmony comes after his inſtrument, whether it be Harpe, or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:181123:10"/>Violl, neither hath it any commaund in the ſame, it neither moueth nor moderateth it; and ſo ſoone as by any occaſion the conſent of the well tuned ſtrings is diſſolued and ended, the Harmony is alſo diſſolued: and vpon euery change by note, it is either higher or lower: but in the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and temperament of the parts, it is otherwiſe. For the ſoule appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not, nor is any other, then it was vpon the alteration of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature thereof. And whereas the body is ſometime changed vpon of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, yet for all that the ſoule abideth, albeit we ſee that the Harmony is diſtempered and out of courſe: and euery temperament may at will be changed, but no man can change his ſoule, before life changeth Who then will ſay that Fortune is a harmony, no not of the body thereto belonging, which is therefore called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or <hi>Diſimilar,</hi> becauſe it hath not all his parts of one kinde and likeneſſe in each point? Forme is a certaine compoſition of formes of the ſame kinde, and that haue ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude among themſelues, which ſeeme to be ſo apt and knit together in themſelues, that they conſpire together in one, and doe agree without diſcord: for it is ridiculous to thinke that the Soule or Forme doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of the bond and compoſition of the different parts, as doth the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect body. But it muſt needes be, that there is one ſimple Forme of the whole compound, which differing from the Formes of the ſimple parts, keepeth them ſound, whole, and incorrupted in the totall. This is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the large teſtimony of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> in his ſixt of <hi>Metaphiſickes,</hi> in theſe words, or to this effect: <hi>That which conſiſteth of any thing, is ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, that the whole vniuerſall is one, not like a heape, but as a ſillable, a ſillable is not the element it ſelfe, neither is it the ſame that</hi> (a) <hi>and</hi> (b) <hi>is, no more is fleſh, fire, and earth.</hi> The Elements diſſolued, theſe are not fleſh, nor ſillable: but the Elements are earth and fire, therefore a ſillable is not an Element or principle, a vocall letter, and mute, but a certaine other thing: ſo in like manner, fleſh is not onely fire and earth, or hot and colde, but alſo another thing. Many other places <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hath, wherein he expoundeth himſelfe more plainely. But when he diſputeth againſt <hi>Empedocles</hi> concerning the ſoule, he ſheweth why there is ſome new beginning and cauſe brought to the formes of ſimples, affirming, that ſimples, eſpecially ſuch as are contrarie, cannot be contained, and conioyne in one, except it be as it were by a very ſtraight bond, leaſt they being diſperſed, ſhould be ſoone diſtracted, and ſo returne thither, from whence euery of them proceeded. Moreouer, he writing concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſoule, againſt <hi>Plato,</hi> ſheweth by the ſame reaſon, that if thoſe things which are many and different, doe conioyne into one and the ſame, it muſt needes be that they are conſtrained ſo to conioyne by the force of another, and to be contained, leaſt they paſſe away. Whereby it is plainely vnderſtood, that as the body albeit compounded of many, yet we call it one: ſo we muſt ſay, that the forme thereof is one, and a ſimple forme. Thus you ſee it followeth neceſſarily, that the formes of compound bodies muſt be ſimple.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:181123:11"/>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alexander</hi> ſaith, that the body worketh by the ſoule: euen as the earth by her waight is caried downward: as if the ſoule were the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the acting body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>But <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> is of a contrary opinion, affirming that the bodies of all things, as well of liuing things as of plants, are the Inſtruments of the ſoule, and were made for the ſame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alexander</hi> ſubiecteth the ſoule, and the whole forme of a thing to the body, and maketh it inferiour to the ſame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>But <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and all the beſt Philoſophers, appoint the ſoule to be more excellent, and farre ſuperiour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alexander</hi> teacheth, that the body is the cauſe and beginning of all action and motion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>But <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> collecting reaſons againſt <hi>Empedocles,</hi> ſheweth, why forme (which he ſimply calleth nature) is the cauſe and the beginning of the motion of all things. To which of theſe will you encline, to <hi>Alexander,</hi> or to <hi>Ariſtotle?</hi> which of theſe ſway moſt with you? If you regard not that famous name, yet reſpect his reaſons, which if you finde more ſtrong and euident then thoſe of <hi>Alexander,</hi> then embrace them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I rather ſubſcribe to <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> then to <hi>Alexander:</hi> but be it as you ſay, that the forme of euery thing is a certaine ſimple ſubſtance, and that it is the chiefe efficient cauſe of functions and faculties, and more excellent then the body, which it vſeth as an inſtrument to execute thoſe functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and offices: yet neuertheleſſe, that ſame forme ſeemeth to come from the temperament of the body, as a certaine ſimple force proceeding from temper, and an accorded harmony of the ſubiect bodies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Is not that which <hi>Alexander</hi> calleth the forme of a naturall thing a ſubſtance? I make no queſtion but that <hi>Alexander</hi> and your ſelfe will and doe confeſſe it. Which granted, you will not denie that the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature of the mixed Elements, and the whole ſtate and power of the ſubiect ariſing here-hence, to be in the kinde of qualities.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>It muſt needes be ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>But a ſubſtance cannot ariſe from one or moe qualities.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>It cannot in any wiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:181123:11"/>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>How then can it be that the forme of a thing ſhould proceede from the mixture and temperament of qualities, and that qualities alone ſhould ingender a ſubſtance, without the concourſe and helpe of a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>A mixture and temper of qualities, is not made of quality alone, but out of that confuſion and mixture of ſuch formes as are the Elements.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>But <hi>Alexander</hi> hath referred the formes of Elements vnto a kinde of qualities, by reaſon whereof he maketh the forme of the compound, to ariſe and ſpring from the qualities.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>For my part I aſſent not to <hi>Alexander</hi> herein, but rather to <hi>Auerrhois,</hi> who placed the formes of Elements, in an ambiguous and doubtfull kinde. What letteth then but that the forme of the whole compound, may ſpring from the formes of ſimple ſubiects?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe ſo the forme ſhall not be ſimple, but as the body is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, ſo alſo the forme ſhall be compound.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I perceiue that as yet you vnderſtand not any meaning.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe I am of opinion, that a ſimple forme may ariſe out of the temperature of the ſubiect formes: which albeit it be ſimple, yet it may comprehend, as it were, in her boſome, the formes of all things.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Then all things whatſoeuer haue flowed together to the procreation of a naturall thing, whether ſimple or compound bodies, the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch time as they were compounded in themſelues by naturall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hauing euery of them both matters, and formes, as alſo their quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties reſiding in them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>It is confeſſed that the Elements being furniſhed with thoſe three, doe come and ioyne together for the procreation of things. What then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Their commixtion being true and exquiſite, thoſe qualities are dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed altogether into the whole: but their matters cannot be totally mingled, but the parts being reduced thither, by a long partition, in ſuch wiſe that now at the laſt they being very ſmall, and bound together with a certaine coniunction betweene themſelues, doe cleaue and agree together.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:181123:12"/>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I hold this neceſſarie. For if there ſhould be a totall confuſion of the matters, the bodies would vtterly periſh in themſelues: which ſeemeth to me ſo abſurd, as it is to be reiected.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>But the formes doe neuer forſake their matters whereunto they are once infuſed: neither can they interchangeably paſſe one into another. Therefore there can be no other mixture of formes, then there is of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Nor yet doe the formes (leauing their ſtates) paſſe away, whereby they being diſſolued from the matter, may mingle themſelues one with another apart, but are ſetled in ſubiects, and are mutually affected one to the other. Wherefore as the whole matters cannot paſſe fully one into the other totally, ſo no more can the formes. Whereupon I inferre, that the forme cannot be ſimple, which commeth out of ſuch a tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and ſo alſo I conclude, that the forme of a naturall thing is a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſubſtance.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Pray you let me heare your opinion more at large, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the forme of a compound body, which is ſimple and ſimilar, be defuſed through the whole body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall heare my ſentence herein, ſo briefely as I can: one naturall ſpirit which is altogether like it ſelfe, is diſperſed and diffuſed throughout this liuing plant which you beholde, &amp; by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming betweene of this ſpirit, one ſoule is ſeated &amp; abideth in the whole plant. This is to be ſeene more plainely in ſenſible creatures, which haue one ſimple and naturall ſpirit, iſſuing from one ſimple fountaine euer like itſelfe, containing not onely the ſimilar, but alſo the diſſimilar parts. Seeing therefore the ſame is one, flowing from a ſimple foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, it cannot be the chariot and bond, but of one ſimple ſoule. For ſo (if the Philoſophers haue ſaid truly, that the ſoule is retained in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, by the bond of his proper and conuenient ſpirit) wee ſhall rightly gather out of the differences of their Spirits, how manifold the eſſences of Soules are, and how diſagreeing among themſelues. Therefore it is concluded, that the naturall Soule is one, breathing and diffuſed into all parts of the body. The like reaſon is of the vitall and feeling facultie, which alſo is one and euery where, as is the animall Spirit: and the ſame alſo muſt neceſſarily be one through all the inſtruments both of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as alſo of motion: and thus I hope you vnderſtand my meaning.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:181123:12"/>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I heare your words, but I craue pardon for my ſlow conceit, in that as yet I vnderſtand not your meaning. For admit that there is one foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine as well of the naturall ſpirit as of the ſoule, yet according to the varying nature of the parts, theſe ſhall be found very much different. There is a certaine peculiar ſpirit and ſoule proper to the bone, to the fleſh, to the ſinew, and ſo to euery particular, for as theſe parts are in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance much vnlike, ſo is it conuenient that theſe ſhould be nouriſhed and encreaſed after an vnlike manner. How then can it be that one and the ſame ſoule can giue and performe things ſo diuers?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Why not? ſeemeth it ſtrange to you and incredible, if by the helpe of ſuch different inſtruments, it ſhew forth many and different effects? this is the thing which in this matter I would you ſhould vnderſtand, that the varying and much differing functions of the parts, come not from the difference of the ſoule it ſelfe, but from the difference of the parts whereunto it is diffuſed and ſpread, therefore after this manner the animall power, albeit it is one and euer the ſame, diſtributed throughout all the nerues, muſcles, and arteries of the body, yet it effecteth and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth by ſome ſence onely; and by other ſome, both ſence and motion: and both of theſe ſometime obſcurely, and ſometime more plainely, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the variety and different affection of the parts into which it is infuſed, and which it moueth. In like manner the naturall power which is in the fleſh begetteth fleſh: that which is in bone, begetteth bone, and ſo of the reſt: for it applieth it ſelfe vnto the temperament of the parts, which it moderateth and nouriſheth, and alſo to the nature and manifold varying vſes thereof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I would gladly be further inſtructed by you in this one thing, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the formes of the parts be a certaine preparation to the ſimple forme of the whole.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>There is no doubt, but that the formes of all the parts in particular, are as it were certaine degrees, by which they are aduanced to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt forme of the whole, neither are they for any other cauſe engraffed into the ſubiect, but to make way by this preparation to bring in that ſupreame forme. Nor yet am I of opinion, that the ſame ſupreame forme was made to preſerue the formes of the ſingular parts, but that rather it conſiſteth for itſelfe and the off-ſpring, or generation thereof: but for as much as the ſame hath a coherence out of all the parts, it commeth therefore to paſſe, that when it defendeth it ſelfe and the whole proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie with this nouriſhment, and with a new fruit or off-ſpring, it mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplieth in ſuch wiſe, that it doth alſo keepe the very formes of the parts incorrupted (whereof it hath neede for preparation) and doth alſo ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time beget new formes: ſo that the parts doe bring much to the forme
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:181123:13"/>of the whole; yet no eſſence but a preparation, and a certaine conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient diſpoſition of receiuing and keeping the whole, and to execute all the functions and offices thereof. For it ioyneth it ſelfe proſperouſly with theſe meane agents, and ſo the wedlocke of the forme, with the whole ſubiect, remaineth indiſſoluble: the which peraduenture being forcibly expulſed, there muſt of neceſſity either preſently follow a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce, or elſe the forme muſt be left idle, and without efficacie in the ſubiect. As therefore the ſubiect of the bone, ſinew, or fleſh, and of euery ſimilar, is not prepared onely out of the temperament of the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, but alſo out of the mixture of the naturall principles, and the forme of the ſinew or bone floweth vnto them, they keeping their formes: ſo we muſt thinke that the body is ſubiect to the forme of the whole liuing creature, framed and builded out of the bone, ſinew, fleſh, and ſuch like parts adhering and mixed in one. For thoſe parts which are called or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganical, doe ariſe from an apt &amp; neate poſition, number, figure, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude of the ſimilars: out of whoſe conueniencie and mutuall conſent, a perfect body at the laſt is made. Therefore all theſe aptly ioyning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one, the ſubiect fitly prepared, draweth vnto it the common forme of all theſe, preſerueth it, and attendeth the functions thereof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſeemeth then, that there are diners ſorts of preparations of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to make it apt and fit for forme.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>There are ſundry preparations, but eſpecially three. One is a good and conuenient temper, which muſt be in euery ſimple and ſimilar part, proceeding from the mixture of the firſt principles, and a good diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole body: another preparation, is a fit and conuenient compoſition, a conſent, and conformation, which we ſee to be ſeuerally in euery organicall part, and in all the members of the body: the third is, a certaine ſpirit diffuſed throughout the whole body, which muſt haue in it a vitall and preſeruing heate.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſee no reaſon, why you ſhould bring in this laſt for a preparation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>If you know that euery liuing creature doth containe heate in it ſelfe, nouriſhing it, whereby life is preſerued, and which being extinct, the ſoule thereof departeth, then haue you no cauſe to doubt, but that the ſame ſpirituall heate is of all other moſt neceſſarie to maintaine life, for that it commeth moſt neere to the nature of the ſoule, and is vnto it a perpetuall and inſeparable companion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>What letteth then, that this preparation may not proceede from the compoſition of the Elements?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Albeit, the firſt preparation before ſpoken of, proceedeth from the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:181123:13"/>Elements, yet the conformation and ſpirit doe not take their originall from thence, but from a more diuine beginning.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe by no meanes it can come to paſſe, that the Elements how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer tempered in the beſt manner, can by themſelues without the helpe of another, giue to the body apt conformation, ſenſe, and motion. For what order or meaſure can you preſcribe in the effecting of theſe things.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>In my opinion, the manner of tempering them is inexplicable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>But if this ſeeme inexplicable, you will ſay that the manner of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament in the conformation is farre more inexplicable. For it is well enough knowne, that ſome things are of a hot temperament, becauſe the hot and firie Element doth exceede the other Elements in the mixture. Moreouer, if by touching you ſhall feele that which is colde, ſo to be, then you will coniecture that the colde Element is predominant: But by what reaſon it commeth ſo to paſſe, that this or that is the figure of this or that thing, you can neither expreſſe by words, nor yet conceiue in minde. For we behold many things with our eyes, which albeit they be of one temperament, yet haue they receiued vnlike ſhapes &amp; figures, and contrariwiſe, that ſome things are like in figure, whoſe tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is moſt vnlike in themſelues. Furthermore, that in-ſet ſpirit or heate which is both the worker and band of life, cannot be aſcribed to the temperament of the parts of the body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you open this matter vnto me ſomewhat more plainely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>A liuing creature, being on the ſodaine newly ſlaine, euery of the ſimilar parts doe for a while retaine temperature, and cannot in ſuch a moment be changed and put out of his nature, and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding then, neyther that in-ſet heate nor ſpirit is in thoſe parts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>No meruaile. For the liuing creature and his parts doe therefore die, becauſe that hot and in-ſet ſpirit, which is the conſeruing cauſe of ſoule and life, being ſodainly diſſolued, either vaniſheth, or elſe being extinguiſhed, periſheth. For it is true which <hi>Ariſtotie</hi> ſaith, that when death approacheth to man or beaſt, the body waxeth colde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Hereupon it is concluded, that the in-ſet ſpirit or heate, doth nothing at all appertaine to the reaſon of temperament; and becauſe the ſpirit which is in the greater Arteries, eſpecially is not reckoned among the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:181123:14"/>parts of the body, no more then is the bloud which is ſhut vp in the veines, it muſt therefore neceſſarily follow, that neither that ſpirit nor heate, doth any thing at all appertaine neither to the ſubſtance of the body, nor to the temperament which ariſeth from the Elements of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Wherefore this temperament ſhall not be the efficient, neither of the ſpirit, nor of the conformation: but this conformation muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and proceede from a more Diuine nature. And of this opinion is <hi>Auerrhois.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I remember in deede that <hi>Auerrhois</hi> ſaith, that both the naturall heate and ſpirit that is in vs, commeth no manner of way from the tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rament of the bodily parts, whoſe words are theſe. The parts by nature doe both worke, and are alſo wholy affected, through the heate which is diffuſed in them, differing from that which is gotten from tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for it is found by experience in Anatomies, that in the heart is contained a certaine little vaporous body exquiſitely hot, the which is tranſmitted from thence by the pipes of the Arteries, and is deriued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the whole body of the liuing creature. Theſe things make plaine to me, that the heate and ſpirit which is naturally in vs, doth not onely not retaine the nature and condition of fire; but alſo that they proceede not from the compoſition and mixture of the Elements, they hauing rather a certaine originall more Diuine: which originall, what manner of thing it ſhould be, neither can I call to minde where he expreſſed it, nor yet can fully attaine vnto it, doe what I can. For this cauſe I pray you ſupply my want herein, which I know you are well able to doe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>You demaund of mee a very hard and doubtfull matter, yea ſuch a thing as for my willingneſſe herein, may cauſe me to be hammered on the Anuile of calamity, and to be accounted too raſh: yet toſatisfie your requeſt, I will reueale vnto you my whole knowledge concerning this matter: firſt, therefore I will begin to ſhew the opinion of ſuch as are learned, and are louers of truth, concerning heate and ſpirit: then I will ſhew you the root and originall of formes, wherein I will ſo deale, that what I lay downe for this point, ſhall be eſpecially builded and founded vpon the ground of <hi>Hippocrates, Plato, Galen,</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> Know therefore firſt of all, that whatſoeuer liueth (and not created of corrupt and filthy matter) proceeded from a ſubiect, which is the proper ſeede of euery thing. Here-hence all the parts of the body are made at the firſt by the force of nature, as it were by the hands of the worke-maiſter: the leſſer and more ſmall parts being at the firſt confuſed, are afterward digeſted and brought into order. So that the ſeede being as it were endued with a certaine excellent artificiall wiſedome, giuing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Plants and other vegetables, which come out of the earth, (which notwithſtanding is mixed with other Elements) and to liuing creatures, which come out of their materiall bloud, their familiar and conuenient
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:181123:14"/>nouriſhment, ſuch as by vſe appertaineth vnto them, together alſo with a fit and equall temperament of the Elements, bringing to paſſe that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one ſingularly and particularly is of this or that temperament (which ſome call the propriety of temperament) and alſo the conformation and compoſition of the ſubiect, is brought both to the whole body, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the parts thereof, by the faculty and power of the ſeed. Thus haue I deliuered vnto you the two firſt orders of preparation, according to my former diuiſion. But the third preparation which is made by the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall heate and ſpirit, as it could not be finiſhed by the contemperament of the Elements onely: ſo more plainely and euidently then the reſt, it taketh originall and beginning at the ſeede. For all men conſtantly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that the ſeede is full with heate and ſpirit, and that it taketh ſuch force from the Parents: for the Parents intending to procreate and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get ſomething like vnto themſelues, are preuented by death; and doe faile before the ſame commeth to light (as ſometime it hapneth to ſeeds and plants, after they are ſowne and grafted) prouident and induſtrious nature ſeeking the eternity of things, looke what power and faculty was in the Parents, to giue life and procreate, the ſame hath ſhe committed to a ſmall portion of ſeede, to bring forth the like by heate and ſpirit. Let this for the preſent ſatisfie thy appetite, another time you ſhall haue more.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou ſaid before, that power is a certaine preparation of Matter, to receiue a certaine forme: ſhew me now ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I pray you, whether theſe preparations (which you ſay be in the ſeede) are the ſame power or no?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>They are without all controuerſie, and doe returne into one and the ſame, but for as much as there is nothing more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the ſaying of the Philoſophers, then this word <hi>(power)</hi> nor more vehemently diſputed of, canſt thou <hi>Philadelph,</hi> ſhew mee how many wayes it is taken.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>If I be not deceiued, I can.<note place="margin">The name of <hi>power</hi> diuerſly taken. 5. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph. cap.</hi> 12. <hi>et</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2. 2. <hi>de Anima. cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> firſt of all defined Power to be the beginning of motion and of alteration, and for as much as the ſame is two-folde, the one of effecting, and the other of ſuffering, hee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon decreed, that there were two ſorts of power: ſaying, that the power of effecting is the beginning of mutation in another (whereof hee hath ſpoken much in his ſeauenth of <hi>Phiſickes</hi>) and the power of ſuffering is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:181123:15"/>the beginning of mutation from another.<note place="margin">In cata. qualita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. <hi>9.</hi> Meta. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> By which ſignification of the word, he calleth the matter of euery thing, <hi>power:</hi> and the forme he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>act</hi> and <hi>perfection.</hi> Both of theſe are in the kinde of ſubſtances. And for this cauſe ſomewhat is drawne to accidents, which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> is wont to call naturall power or impotencie. For it is an hability or affection, by whoſe helpe euery thing either doeth or ſuffereth. Or if you pleaſe, it is a certaine diſpoſition or readineſſe to doe or to ſuffer ſomething to be done. And thus he called all Arts, powers of acting, becauſe they are the beginning of changing in another. The like affections alſo he ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to things that haue no life, by the helpe whereof they doe either worke more ſpeedily, or elſe doe withſtand and ſtop, leaſt by the force of the contraries they be changed into that which is worſe: the power of ſuffering is a certaine <hi>Diatheſis,</hi> whereby euery thing is readily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted into another ſtate.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Strike ſaile, and anchour here a while: for now you are come into your wiſhed Hauen. For the matter which we debate of now, is the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of ſuffering, which being in the matter as a certaine preparation, maketh the ſame apt and fit for commutation and change.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>This is that power which <hi>Alexander Aprodiſaeus</hi> ſaid, was the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning put into matter, whereby it was apt to take all things vpon it, which ſhould come out of it or from it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>They which haue defined power to be a certaine preparation and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of matter, (albeit they thought it not fit to ſeeke further what manner of preparation that ſhould be) yet doe thruſt vpon vs a prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious falſe inuention, and doe rather buſie themſelues about the name, then ſeeke to know the things themſelues.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you reſolue me yet further concerning one doubt, the which alſo is full of obſcurity to many. Whereas the Philoſophers ſay, that Forme is brought out of the power of the matter: doe you thinke that theſe preparations when they haue receiued full perfection, doe put from themſelues Forme? I know that <hi>Simplicius</hi> hath ſo written con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this point, in theſe words. Nothing perfect commeth from that which is imperfect, except power comming as a meane betweene, addeth that which is wanting to perfection, taking chiefe perfection from that which is moſt perfect. I doubt not but theſe words of <hi>Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius</hi> are true, yet I learne nothing by them. Others teach me that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is a certaine quality which extendeth it ſelfe very farre both wayes, obſcure and very little in the beginning, but ſoone after it getteth ſtrength, and waxeth greater by little and little, and ſo by ſmall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe it commeth at the laſt to full perfection. And then it is that <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telechia,</hi> according to <hi>Aristotle,</hi> which ſome call perfection, and others a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:181123:15"/>certaine continuall agitation. As therefore this perfection ſeemeth to be finiſhed by little and little from an imperfect and obſcure preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo the forme of euery thing (which differeth nothing from perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) doth ſpring and ariſe from preparation and power: For ſay they, perfection is Forme; and preparation power: ſo that as at the laſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration is made perfection, ſo power is changed into forme.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Take heede <hi>Philadelph,</hi> that you be not here enſnared and decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, there are many falſe things which ſeeme true, which couered with the cloake of truth, ſeduce many through ſalſhood, into foule and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full errours, for this which you haue now deliuered, is a very ſubtill point, that perfection is the forme of a thing: which if you hold and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, you erre groſly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>How then? doe you thinke that there is difference betweene theſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Very great difference, euen as great as is the difference of kindes. Perfection commeth from power, and is by little and little conſuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as is a young man to perfect age, and the part goeth before the whole, but the whole forme which ſucceedeth is on the ſodaine, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of before there was not the leaſt mite. Perfection, is a certaine patient nature, as is power. Forme is a nature efficient, and the beginning of all motion. Perfection is onely an accident: but Forme is a ſimple and pure ſubſtance. How then can it be, that power, by the degrees of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, ſhould paſſe into a ſollide and expreſſe forme, and ſo of a quality to be made a ſubſtance? as if the <hi>genera ſuprema,</hi> which haue no manner of conuenience with themſelues, and which are more farre diſtant, then are the things which are moſt contrarie, ſhould mutually paſſe one into another? I denie not but that one qualitie may be changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another, and one ſubſtance into another, becauſe they haue one common matter: but that in like ſort qualitie may be changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſubſtance, no thought of mans minde can comprehend and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Giue mee leaue to propound againſt you that which is holden by ſome concerning this point: who ſay, that the power which is in the ſeede, is encreaſed by little and little, vntill it come to full perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>But I pray you tell mee, by what acting force and prouoking power doe they ſay that encreaſe is giuen?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alexander</hi> anſwereth you, that firſt there is infuſed into the ſeed a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine beginning of motion, which by a force taken from the begetting,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:181123:16"/>acteth vntill it come to ſome end, and vntill by a continuing encreaſe it hath perfected it ſelfe, and as it were entring the race, ceaſeth not vntill it come to the marke and end thereof, vnleſſe it be forcibly ſtayed in the courſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>You obiect and ſay, that there is giuen to the begetting ſeede a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine force and beginning of motion. Doe they vnderſtand that this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of motion is power?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes verily, they doe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>And doe they ſay that the ſame beginning which is power, doth acte continually, and that it doth proceede from the firſt entred natures, to the laſt conſumated, whereunto nothing can be added, which we denie to be the higheſt and moſt perfect.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>They doe ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>And doe they conſtantly affirme that this power is a quality.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>They affirme that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>But no quality can at the firſt and by it ſelfe, act; but euery action belongeth to the forme that hath gotten ſubſtance, which is a certaine efficient beginning.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>They denie not this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Seeing therefore they ſay, that power is encreaſed by little and little, vntill a perfect forme be made, to what forme ſhall it firſt of all be aſcribed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>You muſt herein anſwere your ſelfe, for I can goe no further.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Wee ſay that in ſeede there are onely three things, namely, Matter, Forme, and Power. Doth then that action of power leade at the firſt to the forme of ſeede?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Whereto elſe ſhould it leade?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>But that cannot be.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>What is the cauſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe whatſoeuer acteth, acteth to this end, that he may make the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:181123:16"/>Patient obiect like himſelfe: neither doth the forme which is in the ſeede intend any other thing, but that it may generate another ſeed out of it ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I knew this well enough before, but the conſequence of the matter, hath enforced me not to denie it. Now therefore I giue place: and yet I affirme, that the power which is in ſeede doth encreaſe it ſelfe by his owne force: neither doth it deſire any externall helpe. For albeit the ſame power is thought to be a quality, yet is it of a more high degree then are others: for the which cauſe <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hath called the ſame a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall power,</hi> becauſe as it is partaker of quality, ſo alſo after a ſort it is alſo partaker of Nature. Wherefore in my opinion, who ſo ſaith that the ſame can doe any thing of it ſelfe, ſhall vtter no abſurdity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe are wonderfull ſhifts; be of what opinion you will, onely know this: If power doe act at the firſt, and by it ſelfe, when it encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth and finiſheth it ſelfe, it bringeth no other thing to paſſe, but ſuch another power as it is it ſelfe: neither can it though it be encreaſed, bring forme out of it ſelfe. Out of the ſeed, as out of the ſubiect, is ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered a liuing creature, or a plant: but there was neuer any in the ranke of the beſt Philoſophers, which held that powers ſhould make forme, or that a liuing creature is generated by the force of ſeede.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>And why ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>That which is not yet, but ſhall be hereafter, is not now ſimply in being: but how can that which is not, be ſaid to beget any other thing? How then thinke you can it come to paſſe, that the power which is in ſeede ſhould procreate forme, if as yet the ſame forme be not in it? Or that the ſeede which is not yet that liuing creature, ſhould effect a liuing creature? For if any thing be to be begotten out of theſe, there muſt be ſome other thing put of neceſſitie, which in act may obtaine forme, and which may be the firſt efficient and chiefe cauſe of this procreation. The which when <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> deepely conſidered, hee decreed that there was a two-fold nature in the procreation of liuing creatures, and of their off-ſpring. One more imperfect which is made in ſeede, and is not yet: Another more perfect, which being in act, is ſimply ſuch an effectrix, as it is in that from whence the ſeede did ſpring. The place is in the ſecond booke, concerning the procreation of liuing creatures; where he putteth a difference betweene Nature and Art, in theſe words: Art is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and the forme of that which is effected: but yet in another: The motion of Nature is in that which is effected, proceeding from another nature, which in act obtaineth the forme. Therefore he holdeth, that a nature is in the ſeede, by which it is made, and moued: and the efficient nature in that which is in act. This ſentence <hi>Simplicius</hi> hath
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:181123:17"/>expounded more largely in theſe words, or to this effect: the nature and cauſe of euery motion, maketh a ſubiect like it ſelfe, and not another: for as the nature of man maketh a man: ſo the nature of ſeede can make nothing but ſeede. For how ſhall that properly make a man which is in the ſeede, which as yet is not the nature of man, before ſuch time as the man be made. If the nature of the ſeede deſireth to be changed, and to haue a liuing creature perfected, then properly the efficient and next cauſe, is the paternall and maternall nature: for the forme goeth before the act in the father and mother, according to the which forme, that which is in power is brought to act. And by this meanes the nature of that which is generated, if it be ſaid to be efficient, it is ſo efficient that the ſame is therewithall made. And that nature hath properly the force of effecting, which is ſuch in act, becauſe nature is the procreatrix of that which is like it ſelfe. Thus <hi>Philadelph,</hi> you ſee that the force of the ſeed which we ſay is called power, cannot be turned into the forme of a liuing creature, how well ſo euer it fitteth it ſelfe, or adorneth it ſelfe, but there muſt be preſent a certaine thing, as is ſuch in act.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe things which you haue now vttered ſeeme in my Iudgement moſt true. But before you finiſh this matter, it is conuenient that you explaine one thing, which all Philoſophers haue approued, namely, that the forme of euery thing is brought forth out of the power of the ſubiect.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>When the power which is in the ſeed, that is to ſay, when the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to bring in forme is come by daily encreaſe to full perfection, it hath alſo obtained therewithall the forme of ſubſtance. For forme ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily followeth that perfection, and neuer leaueth it. For this cauſe <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> calleth Forme oftentimes by the name of <hi>Entelechia</hi> in regard of perfection: either becauſe it is an inſeperable companion of perfect power, or elſe becauſe it doth fulfill and perfect it wholy. Therefore as we ſay that perfection, ſo alſo according to vſuall ſpeech, we ſay that forme is brought out of the power of the matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Then it ſeemeth to me that forme is extracted out of the precurrent power, no otherwiſe then act commeth out of the habit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>The compariſon which you haue made is fit to the purpoſe, for by long cuſtome and vſe, a Muſitian or Harper, hauing gotten a habit in deuiding his parts on his Inſtrument, looſeth not that habit, though he fleepe, but can readily when he awaketh ſhew his former skill, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his owne will. Therefore as the act proceedeth from the habit or skill, becauſe the act cannot ſhew forth it ſelfe, except the habit be firſt perfectly gotten: ſo in like manner it fareth in the procreation of things: For it is not Power that imprinteth the forme, but an externall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:181123:17"/>cauſe, which notwithſtanding being without the helpe of power, ſhould not haue ſtrength enough of it ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I perceiue you well, it is as if one hauing Science vſeth it not: yet when he hath will to make vſe thereof, he contemplateth, and is in act a man of Science: euen ſo what ſubiect ſo euer hath perfect power to beget a thing when the externall force of the agent commeth, the ſame hath preſent action and forme. And hereunto agreeth <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who ſaith: he which knoweth any thing, if he haue his minde actually oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in contemplation, yet he keepeth his habit, and hath not loſt his Science in contemplating, but doth rather amend and perfect it, euen ſo, that which hath receiued perfect power, when the forme commeth, putteth not off the quality of power, but addeth thereto an ornament &amp; a perfection. Thus you ſee, I wel vnderſtand you, not peruerting your meaning, I will now briefly repeate what hath beene ſpoken hetherto for my better memorie, and alſo to let you ſee how well I haue obſerued for my further knowledge, that which at my requeſt you haue deliuered to this effect following.<note place="margin">A briefe repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all that hath beene ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</note> Of all the things which the parent <hi>Nature</hi> hath brought forth, the firſt conſtitution is made out of the inferiour and ſubiect matter and forme: of the which two, for as much as forme is farre the more excellent, it is more often called forme then matter. And as we doe ſee that the thing begotten, is nothing permanent or ſtable; but doth ſometime fall and vaniſh away: ſo that forme, by which the thing did flouriſh, cannot perpetually abide and cleaue to the matter, but remoueth it ſelfe ſometime, and that very ſodainly, which ſhall be the deſtruction thereof. But before forme came into matter, it deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a certaine ornature and preparation of the ſame, without the which it cannot enter there. This preparation is called Power, the which power is not ſo much as a portion, nor the leaſt mite of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching forme, but onely a fore-running preparation, or ordering of the matter. Whatſoeuer hath begotten any thing, is thought to haue employed and beſtowed this power: ſometime by it ſelfe, alone, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time with the ſeed, or with a certaine Seminarie, agreeing and anſwering thereto. Therefore ſeeing power is a manifold and varying preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the body, both out of thoſe foure incorrupt beginnings of things which are the Elements, with the temper made in the ſmalleſt proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and wholy annexed together, and a feat and comely conformation of the body, with an apt coniunction of the parts therewith, as alſo all commoderation and conueniencie of the naturall and in-ſet ſpirit, this whole order of powers dependeth on the faculties and force of the ſeed, and of him that caſt the ſeed, then when all preparation is fully finiſhed, (which is when power is conſumated) then by a certaine naturall and ineuitable neceſſity, the forme commeth and ſheweth it ſelfe outwardly. This forme is altogether ſimple without any compoſition of the formes of the ſubiects, and yet is able to doe and further many things, according
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:181123:18"/>to the ſeuerall faculties which it hath. They which meaſure all things by the ſenſes, and haue an eye onely to the neereſt cauſe, contend and ſtifly holde, that the forme is ſtirred vp, and brought forth from out of the power of the matter, which opinion they defend with ſtrong argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. For the efficient or genitorie, when he begetteth another thing of his name or kinde, by himſelfe, or by the meanes of his ſeed or ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie, doth neither make, nor yet put in the forme thereof, but is the cauſe of this concourſe onely, namely, that forme may be in the matter. And this is that which is ſaid to be the cauſe of the begotten, and of the genitour which hath begotten. But yet there is a more high &amp; moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent workmaiſter, who giueth forme outwardly by a certaine inſpired motion. This is the ſumme which hath bin hetherto ſpoken for my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I commend your memory, and collection, in this repetition.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y that which hath beene hitherto diſcourſed, it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that three things are in the compoſition of euery na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall thing, to wit, <hi>Matter, Forme,</hi> &amp; <hi>Temperament:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of two as principles, namely, <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Forme,</hi> doe make euery thing: but <hi>Temperament</hi> is onely in <hi>Matter,</hi> which <hi>Matter</hi> is congealed and compacted out of the mixture of the firſt Elements of the world. Now therefore declare whether the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers and forces of all things proceeded from theſe three and no more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſpeaking of efficient cauſes, propundeth ſome altogether without reaſon, and ſome endued with reaſon, and therefore ſaith: Whatſoeuer things are the efficients of contrary works, are partakers of reaſon: and euery thing is deuoyd of reaſon, which is the beginning of one worke onely: hereupon I frame this argument. Of the naturall cauſes and faculties which are without reaſon, one cauſe is the beginning of one effect, neither can moe or diuers effects proceede from one and the ſame: but we obſerue and ſee many effects, and the ſame much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and vnlike of euery ſimple and naturall body; therefore theſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be referred to one common beginning, but there muſt needes be many cauſes of theſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Although this one beginning hath diuers cauſes and faculties, yet I aſcribe all thoſe to Temperament; except you ſhew vnto me that of theſe ſome doe proceede from <hi>Matter,</hi> and ſome from <hi>Forme.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:181123:18"/>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt, then I take this as granted from you, that there are certaine forces and faculties in temperament.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Should I denie that which is confirmed by the teſtimonie and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of all Philoſophers?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>And yet Temperament, doth not comprehend in it alone the effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of all functions, but of thoſe onely which after a certaine manner doe retaine and ſet forth the nature and condition of the firſt qualities. For in temperament and mixture it is very neceſſary, that one or two quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties doe excell, which becauſe they are ſuperiour, they challenge vnto them all the efficiencie of temperament, in ſuch wiſe, that whatſoeuer is effected by it, the ſame is ſaid to be perfected by them, albeit the reſt are not idle. For that which we perceiue to be hot, doth heate, albeit more faintly then fire. And that which is hot and dry, doth both heate and dry together. Neither can any function come out of the Temperament, which is not referred to the nature and power of the predominant qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. This if it be alone and pure, ſhall haue the forces of the Element: but if it be tempered with the mixture of the contrary, it ſhall ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſame forces, albeit obſcure and inferiour. For the repugnancie of the contrary may hinder the forces of the predominant quality &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, but it cannot vtterly ſuppreſſe and quaile the nature and ſtrength thereof. Therfore it is neceſſary that the power of the predominant Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doe abide and domineere in the temperament, albeit the ſame po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer be weaker &amp; oppreſſed, which enclining alwaies to the accuſtomed nature, can produce no effect out of another different kinde. And to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you that the rules goe thus, it ſeemeth good to me to vſe a more ſubtill reaſon. The true mixture is of bodies, the temperament is of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities onely. But contrary qualities doe not mutually paſſe into them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or one into another, ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle:</hi> For heate doth not paſſe into colde, nor moiſtneſſe into drineſſe, or contrariwiſe: but the ſubiect body onely doth ſuffer change. For heate is not ſubiect to colde, nor colde to heate, but that which is ſubiect to either, is <hi>Matter.</hi> Therfore if ye thinke that contraries cannot paſſe into themſelues, how ſhall it come to paſſe, that a new power or quality ſhould ariſe out of the contemperament of the chiefe qualities, which hauing gotten a different nature, doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſauour or taſte thoſe chiefe qualities. Wherefore it is neceſſarie that the forces which ariſe out of the principall qualities, doe immitate the nature of the ſuperiour and ruling quality.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſee verely the reaſons of this concluſion. Tell me therfore I pray you, what force of effecting doe you thinke hath the matter gotten at the laſt. For ſeeing it is rude &amp; without forme, &amp; only ſubiect to beare the formes of things, it effecteth nothing at all, but ſuffereth &amp; endureth all order of change.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:181123:19"/>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I doe not hold and determine, that there are any forces and functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the ſimple and bare matter of things, but in that matter which is compounded of mixed ſubſtances of the Elements, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſheweth that of the foure firſt qualities, two, that is to ſay, Heate and Colde, are actiue, and are therefore called efficient: the other two, that is to ſay, Moyſt and Dry, are called paſſiue: ſo in like manner concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the beginnings of nature, <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Ayre</hi> are as cauſes efficient: but water and earth are as the matter patient. That ſame <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth thoſe things which are more potent and excellent in ſtrength, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply efficients; but <hi>Water</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> which are leſſe potent, hee maketh the matter of compound and thicke bodies, and calleth the qualities of theſe drineſſe and moiſtneſſe. Liuing creatures (ſaith he) doe liue and conuerſe onely in the earth, and in the water, and not in the <hi>Aire</hi> and <hi>Fire,</hi> becauſe earth and water are the matters of bodies, and therefore he addeth theſe words: That which ſuffereth is either dry or moiſt, or elſe compounded of both: and for this cauſe water is ſaid to be the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of moiſtneſſe, and earth the body of drineſſe, becauſe amongſt moiſt and dry things they are moſt paſſiue. Hereof I gather, that moiſtneſſe and drineſſe are patible qualities, and that earth and water, wherein is much moiſtneſſe and drineſſe, are the matter of naturall bodies. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for good conſiderations we do call the ſame, the vertue and quality of matter, which <hi>Aristotle</hi> is wont to call the ſecundarie qualities ariſing from the patible, and alſo calleth them corporall effects, as are hard and ſoft, thicke and thinne, tough and brittle, light and ſharpe, and ſuch like, all which are hidden and contained in matter. Alſo <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the power and qualities of the Elements, calleth them effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, but yet after a more ſubtill manner: but when he conſidereth their ſubſtance, then he affirmeth all of them to be patible, and the matter of naturall bodies, whereof all creatures (which are in the vniuerſall frame of this world) conſiſt. This therefore is the matter of mixt bodies, which being compunded of the matter of the elements, and of the vertue of their qualities, hath the ſame forces, which I called ſecunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and from whence all that is ſoft, hard, thick and thinne, proceedeth. And this is the cauſe why our meates doe nouriſh quicker or ſlower, and why they haue vertue to ſtop, to open, or to cleanſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Your ſpeech importeth thus much (as I take it) as if you ſhould ſay, that ſuch forces doe one while proceede from the qualities of the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſometime from their matter, and yet neuertheleſſe the forces both of the qualities and matter doe apparantly come from the elements themſelues.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>They ſeeme to proceede in deede from both, if as well the one as the other ſeeme Elementarie, but yet except thoſe forces which proceede
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:181123:19"/>from the qualities be diſcerned from thoſe which the matter yeeldeth, there will no doubt be great ambiguity in things, and much confuſion, which if you thinke good to cleare and auoid, you ſhall driue the effects of the elements from the temperament, and the effects of the conſiſtence from the matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I like the diſtinction of your <hi>Homonomye:</hi> now therefore proceede with the third ſort of forces, namely, of that which concerneth forme.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>If the forme of a naturall thing, which is the perfection of the whole, be farre more excellent than either the matter or the tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who I pray you is ſo mad, and ſo blinde in the contemplation of things, as to thinke that matter and temperament, haue their forces and effects, and that forme ſhould be idle, and nothing auaileable in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of acting? That the accidents ſhould haue in it a naturall effecting power, and the ſubſtance, which of all other is moſt chiefe, ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of all acting power to doe any thing, which to thinke is too ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd. I for my part, attribute ſo much force to the formes of bodies, that I verely thinke that all thoſe effects which we behold in the things crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, doe chiefly and eſpecially proceede from them. And the rather I am of this opinion, becauſe <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> confirmeth the ſame. For he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing himſelfe againſt certaine Philoſophers, which deduced the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of naturall bodies, from hot and colde, thinking that all things were made of theſe, and by theſe, makeeh it plaine by demonſtration, that thoſe qualities are onely inſtruments of a certaine more ſuperiour and principall cauſe, which hee hath expreſſed by the name of nature. For whoſoeuer ſhall affirme that theſe ſecundarie qualities haue the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue in themſelues to worke, and ſhall attribute the cauſe &amp; power, as it were, of acting to the Axe, or ſuch like inſtrument, and ſo the forme and perfection of the thing reiected, ſhall paſſe by the true cauſe, impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that to the actions of the Inſtrument, which neuertheleſſe ſhould remaine idle, if they were not moued &amp; ſtirred vp by the force of forme, the ſame I ſay ſhall much forget himſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>If there be ſo great force &amp; power in forme, that to the ſame chiefly all motion and action muſt be imputed, then ſhall wee be enduced to thinke, that the functions and qualities which euen now you referred to temperament and matter, take not their originall by themſelues, but firſt from forme. What cauſe haue you then to determine, that they proceede from temperament and matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>They which ſoare no higher then the wing of common ſenſe doe carie them, will affirme that ſuch functions and qualities ſpring from matter and temperament, albeit forme hath the firſt place and prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence: we following theſe mens low pitch of conceit, affirme that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:181123:20"/>thoſe qualities proceede from Matter and Temperament, becauſe they are effected by theſe as by inſtruments. But what qualities and faculties I ſimply pronounce to be of forme, thoſe I affirme to haue no neede of the helpe of Inſtrument.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Goe to then: Are not matter and temperament which you propund as Inſtruments, certaine furtherances &amp; forces of the efficient forme?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>No verely. But as in any artificiall worke, the Caruer or Smith is he which is the firſt and principall agent, and who hath the power and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of acting, (which is his Art and ſtrength of body) but the Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers inſtrument, as Axe, or Hammer, is but an helper, and in the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there is as it were a certaine borrowed helpe or force, not which worketh, but by which the worke is the better effected, and to this end the well faſhioned and ſharpe Toole is a great furtherance: euen ſo in like manner almoſt, in the naturall working of things, whereby they are brought to paſſe, <hi>Forme</hi> is the firſt and chiefe efficient, hauing in it the effecting power: But Matter and Temperament, are as helping inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the efficient cauſe, and either of theſe, to wit, Matter and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament, haue their power and faculty, and an apt conſtitution, by which the effect may more eaſely be brought to paſſe. Therefore in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie naturall body, there are three efficient cauſes, namely, Forme, Matter, and Temperament, euery of which haue their peculiar force, whereby it worketh ſtrongly or after a weake manner Forme of it ſelfe is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of working, neither doth it borrow any thing of the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to haue being, or the nature of beginning, which commeth after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as by acceſſarie meanes. <hi>Forme</hi> therefore had the power and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of acting, before ſuch time as it acted by the Inſtrument, euen as the Caruer before he worke any thing with his Toole, hath ability and Art to effect, the which faculty he taketh not from his Toole or Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Whereby it appeareth, that the faculty which is naturally in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie forme, and which is called the property thereof, is farre different from Matter and Temperament in force and vertue: for a Caruer or Painter by his Science onely, (which is his faculty) without the helpe of any Inſtrument can make an Image in his minde: ſo in like manner the forme of a thing, effecteth the thing without the helpe of Matter and Temperament. And foraſmuch as theſe three are mixed and conioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in euery naturall body, <hi>Formes</hi> can ſcarſly ſhew forth their forces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and by themſelues in effect, but that therewith Matter and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament will expreſſe their ſupplie. But on the contrary part, Matter and Temperament cannot ſhew forth themſelues without forme: ſo that theſe in their ſeuerall kindes muſt be diſtinguiſhed, and not confounded.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:181123:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our ternarie of <hi>Forme, Matter,</hi> and <hi>Temperament,</hi> putteth me in minde of three principles, which that great and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Philoſopher <hi>Hermes Triſmegistus</hi> hath deliuered, that is to ſay, <hi>Salt, Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercurie;</hi> which three hee appointeth as the onely naturall beginnings of all things created, which agreeth not with <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> foure Elementarie principles. How can theſe two opinions ſo different in number ſtand together?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> had reaſon to appoint a quaternarie of Elements, according to the number of the foure qualities, <hi>hot, colde, drie,</hi> and <hi>moyſt,</hi> as the firſt principles of all things, as is to be ſeene in his ſecond booke of <hi>Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of liuing creatures.</hi> Yet foraſmuch as one can beget nothing of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe but three therfore three doe make one body, by a compound made by a three-fold efficacie of the diuine word. For God in the beginning, as <hi>Moſes</hi> teſtifieth, made of nothing a <hi>Chaos,</hi> deepe, or waters (which we pleaſe to call it) animated with his ſpirit, who being the great workmai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in the creation, ſeparated firſt light from darkneſſe, and this Ethereall <hi>Heauen</hi> which we beholde as a <hi>quarta eſſentia,</hi> or fourth eflence, or moſt pure ſpirit, or moſt ſpiritual ſimple created body. Then be deuided waters from waters: that is to lay, the more ſubtill, aterie, and Mercuriall liquor, from the more thicke, clammy, oyle-like, or Sulfurous liquor. After that, <hi>Moſes</hi> telleth vs that God ſeparated from the more groſſe waters, the <hi>Earth,</hi> which ſtandeth apart by it ſelfe, like <hi>Salt.</hi> And thus in the boſome of the world, God encluded theſe three ſimple bodies, <hi>Salt, Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercurie,</hi> as the firſt formes of things.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Doe the Philoſophers, the followers of <hi>Hermes,</hi> exclude the Element of <hi>Fire,</hi> in the compoſition of bodies elemented?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>In <hi>Geneſis</hi> it is euidently to be ſeene, that there is made mention of Heauen, Earth, and Water onely: but of Fire and Aire, no mention at all, becauſe theſe two are encluded vnder the other: as vnder <hi>Heauen, Fire,</hi> and vnder the ſuperiour waters, <hi>Aire:</hi> ſo that hereby it is plaine, that there is no other fierie element but Heauen; a fourth eſſence, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated out of the more ſubtill matter and forme of the three elements: which being ſo ſeparated and extracted, is no other thing but a pure Aetheriall and moſt ſimple fire, moſt perfect, and farre different from the three Elements, as imperfect, which Fire is the Author of all formes,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:181123:21"/>powers, and actions in all the inferiour things of nature, as the firſt in degree among the ſecond cauſes, and carieth it ſelfe like a Father toward his off-ſpring.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>What are the eſſences of theſe three, <hi>Fire, Aire,</hi> and <hi>Earth?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>The firſt which is fire, is a ſubſtance containing in it life and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or the ſoule of the Elements. The ſecond which is <hi>Aire,</hi> is a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which hath in it the nouriſhing foment of life, and the ſpirit of the Elements. The third is an <hi>Earthie</hi> and <hi>watrie</hi> ſubſtance, both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther carying the body of the Elements, vnder the name of <hi>Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you declare vnto me the complexions and qualities of theſe three principles, <hi>Salt, Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercurie,</hi> that I may vnderſtand how they agree with thoſe of the Elements.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mercurie</hi> is a ſharpe liquor, fluible, and penetrable, and a moſt pure Aethereall and ſubſtantiall body: a ſubſtance <hi>Aierie,</hi> moſt ſubtill, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and full of ſpirit, the ſeede of life, and an eſſentiall forme compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in <hi>Aire. Sulphur</hi> is a moiſt, ſweet, oile-like, clammy originall, which giueth ſubſtance to it ſelfe, the nouriſhment of <hi>Fire,</hi> or of a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heate, endued with the force of molifying, and conioyning toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, comprehended in <hi>water. Salt</hi> is that dry body, ſaltiſh, meerely earthie, repreſenting the nature of <hi>Salt,</hi> endued with wonderfull ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, of diſſoluing, congealing, cleanſing, emptying, and with other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite qualities comprehended in earth. Theſe three principles were called by the fore-ſaid <hi>Hermes, Spirit, Soule,</hi> and <hi>Body; Mercurie, Spirit: Sulphur,</hi> the <hi>Soule,</hi> and <hi>Salt</hi> the <hi>body.</hi> The body is ioyned with the ſpirit by the bond of the <hi>Soule, Sulphur,</hi> for that it hath affinitie with both the extreames, as a meane, coupling them together: For <hi>Mercurie</hi> (as is ſaid) is liquide, thinne, and fluible. <hi>Sulphur</hi> is a ſoft oyle paſſable. <hi>Salt</hi> is dry, thicke, and ſtable: the which three are ſo proportionate together, and tempered one with the other, that there is a great Analogie &amp; conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie in this contrariety of beginnings. For <hi>Sulphur</hi> with his humiditie oyle-like, ioyneth as a meane the two extreames, fixed <hi>Salt,</hi> and flying <hi>Mercurie:</hi> that is to ſay, the drineſſe of <hi>Salt,</hi> and the moiſtneſſe of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie,</hi> are contempered with the viſcous humidity of <hi>Sulphur:</hi> the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Salt,</hi> and the ſubtilty of <hi>Mercurie,</hi> (which are contrary) are tempered with the fluidity of <hi>Sulphur.</hi> Moreouer, <hi>Sulphur</hi> by his excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſweetneſſe, doth contemper the ſharpneſſe or ſowerneſſe of <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> and the bitterneſſe of <hi>Salt:</hi> and by his clammineſſe, doth conioyne the ſubtill flying of <hi>Mercurie,</hi> with the firmeneſſe and ſtability of <hi>Salt.</hi> Thus of theſe three, all naturall bodies are compounded.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſaid before that <hi>Fire</hi> is the Author of all formes and actions in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:181123:21"/>vniuerſall nature. I pray you ſhew vnto me after what manner it is ſo to be reputed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Fire by his winde and ſpirit, carieth and conuayeth his ſeeds into the belly of the earth, whereby the generation &amp; fruit is nouriſhed, foſtered, and groweth, and is at the laſt thruſt forth out of the lap and boſome of the Elements. This Heauen or Fire, albeit it is no complexion in it ſelfe, that is to ſay, neither hot nor colde, moiſt nor dry: yet by his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall diſpoſition it yeeldeth to all things, heate and colde, moiſture and drineſſe. For ſo much as there are ſtarres which haue their moſt colde and moiſt ſpirits, as the <hi>Saturnals</hi> and <hi>Lunaries:</hi> others moſt hot and dry, as the <hi>Solarie</hi> and <hi>Martials:</hi> others hot and moiſt as the <hi>Iouials,</hi> who by their vertues and complexion wherewith euery ſtarre is endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, doe forme, faſhion, and impregnate all theſe inferiour things in ſuch wiſe, that ſome indiuiduals are of that condition and complexion, which they haue borrowed and taken from their framing or faſhioning ſtarre or planet: other ſome of another complexion, which they haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, according to the condition of other ſtarres. For God hath giuen to Heauen moſt perfect and ſimple ſeedes, ſuch as are the Planets and Starres, which hauing in them vitall faculties, and complexions, doe powre them forth into the lap of the inferiour Elements, animating and forming them. Neither doth this Heauen at any time ceaſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor the Aſtrall ſeeds thereof, becauſe their vertues are ſo abundant, that they are neuer exhauſted, nor yet doe they ſuffer alteration or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution of their faculties, wherby they may ceaſe from procreating or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, albeit at ſometime they doe make more or leſſe fruitfull, than at other times. Hereupon commeth that perpetuall circulation, by the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit whereof, the ſeeds of the Elements, or their matter, are coupled with the ſeeds of the ſtarres, thruſting their contained ſeed into the maternall lap, that it may forme &amp; bring forth a kindly off-ſpring. For as Heauen is ſaid to worke vpon the Earth, ſo alſo the inferiour Elements doe yeeld and beſtow their actions and motions, albeit after another manner: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Heauen is altogether actiue and nothing paſſiue, being of a Homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniall and moſt perfect nature, and is therefore incorruptible and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable, vntill the predeſtinate end of things created.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Are then thoſe three, <hi>Salt, Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercurie,</hi> the Eſſentiall and firſt principles of the Heauen?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>God in creating Heauen, ſeparated out of the Chaos, or confuſed Maſſe, the moſt pure from the impure: that is to ſay, he reduced the more pure and Aethereall <hi>Mercurie,</hi> the more pure &amp; inextinguible ſtarres and lights, into a Cryſtaline, &amp; Diamontine ſubſtance, or moſt ſimple body, which is called Heauen, the higheſt &amp; fourth formall Element, that from the ſame the formes, as it were ſeeds, might be powred forth (as is before ſhewed) into the more groſſe Elements to the generation of all things.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:181123:22"/>Therefore it cannot be denied, but that <hi>Heauen</hi> doth conſiſt of thoſe three principles, albeit moſt ſimple: but yet of the moſt pure, ſpirituous, and altogether formall. If wee will beholde the purity of the Heauen aboue other elements, and the conſtancie thereof, looke then vpon thoſe bright and ſhining fires, continually glittering with light, to whom the Heauen hath giuen the moſt pure &amp; in extinguible <hi>Sulphureus</hi> ſubſtance, whereof they conſiſt. For ſuch as the Heauen is in eſſence, ſuch fruits hath it brought forth therein, as touching ſubſtance: out of whoſe vitall impreſſions and influences they procreate and bring forth ſome likeneſſe of themſelues in the more groſſe Elements: but yet according as the matter is more groſſe, more thinne, more durable, more conſtant, or more tranſitorie. And the influences of ſuch fires are Mercuriall ſpirits: but the light and ſhining brightneſſe is <hi>Sulphur:</hi> their fixed Heauens or vitriall Chriſtalline circles is a ſalt body; which circles are ſo pure ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and fixed, that a Diamond which partaketh of the nature of fixed Salt, is not of more purity, continuance, and perpetuity then they are.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſay you to the Element of <hi>Aire?</hi> doth that alſo conſiſt of <hi>Salt, Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercurie?</hi> If it doe, ſhew mee I pray you the manner how?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>The beginnings of <hi>Aire</hi> are all one with the other, but yet more groſſe, leſſe pure, and leſſe ſpirituous and ſimple, then the beginnings ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall, notwithſtanding that they are much more perfect, thinne, and penetrating, than are the waterie and terreſtriall <hi>Mercuries</hi> and <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> and are ſuch, that next to <hi>Heauen, Aire</hi> hath the preheminence of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie and power: whoſe powers and effects, are to be ſeene in diuers and ſundry winds (which are <hi>Mercuriall</hi> fruits) &amp; the ſpirits of the <hi>Aierie</hi> Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whoſe <hi>Sulphurs</hi> alſo are diſcerned to be pure and brght in burning Comets, which are no perpetuall fires and <hi>Sulphurs,</hi> as are the ſtarres, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generating from the nature of them as from purity and ſimplicity, into a more groſſe and impure forme. And as concerning <hi>Earth</hi> in <hi>Aire,</hi> it is ſo ſubtill and thin, that it is very hard to beſeene, being diffuſed through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole Region of the <hi>Aire.</hi> Which <hi>Salt</hi> ſheweth not it ſelfe to mans eye, but in Dewes, and Froſts, and in Manna; In Honey which Bees doe gather from flowers, wherein there is no other thing but <hi>Salt, Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercurie</hi> of the <hi>Aire,</hi> which by a skilfull Chymiſt are ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from it with great admiration. Yea, the ruſticke Coridon findeth this to be true by his experience, in that he can ſeparate the matter of the Bees worke into waxe, a matter ſulphurous: into Honey, which is a Mercuriall eſſence: and into droſſe repreſenting the terreſtriall <hi>Salt.</hi> The very ſame beginnings of <hi>Aire</hi> may alſo be ſeene in Meteors, in Lightnings, in Corruſcations, in Thundrings, and in ſuch like, which are ingendred in the <hi>Aire.</hi> For in that fierie flame which breaketh forth is <hi>Sulphur,</hi> in the windie ſpirit thereof is <hi>Mercurie,</hi> and in the ſtone and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:181123:22"/>thunderbolt is Salt fixed. Thus that ſuperiour ſeparated into an Aethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reall and ayrie <hi>Heauen,</hi> hath his three beginnings, <hi>Salt, Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie,</hi> yet neuertheleſſe very different in ſimplicity and purity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe demonſtrations perſwade much: but ſhew mee I pray you whether the things of this inferiour Globe, conſiſt in eſſence of the ſame number of three, <hi>Salt, Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercurie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe three beginnings doe more plainely ſhew themſelues in this inferiour Globe, by reaſon of their more groſſe matter, which is to our ſight more ſenſible. For out of the Element of Water, the iuyces and metalline ſubſtances doe daily breake forth in ſight, the vapours of whoſe moiſture or more ſpirituous iuyce doe ſet forth Mercurie: the more dry exhalations Sulphur, and their coagulated and congealed matter, Salt. Of the which Salts, Nature doth offer vnto vs diuers ſorts, as Allom, Coperas, Vitriol, Salt Gem, Salt Armoniacke, Salt Peeter, and many others. She giueth alſo vnto vs many kindes of Sulphurs, as Brimſtone, Bitumen, Pitch, Tarre, and ſuch like. Alſo diuers ſorts of Mercuries. Moreouer in the Sea, there are Mercuriall, Airie, and Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurus ſpirits, whoſe Meteors, in <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> and tn other kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led fires, by reaſon of their ſundry Sulphurs and exhalations, doe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the ſame. And as touching the Salt in the Sea, no man will make queſtion, it is ſo ſuperabundant. From this Marine Salt, the Earth being like vnto a ſpunge, and ſucking the ſame continually into it, produceth the afore mentioned Salts, beſide ſtore of minerals and mettals, as the mother and firſt originall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>For as much as theſe three firſt beginnings are in the Heauen, in the Aire, and in the Water (as you haue ſhewed) I haue no reaſon to doubt, but that by a farre greater likelihood, the ſame are to be found in the earth, and to be made no leſſe apparant, ſeeing the earth of all other Elements is the moſt fruitfull and plentifull. Therefore diſcourſe vnto me I pray you, concerning the <hi>Salt, Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercurie,</hi> of Plants and Trees.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>The Mercurial ſpirits of the Earth ſhew themſelues in the leaues and fruits: the Sulphurs in the flowers, ſeeds, and kernels: the Salt in the wood, barke, and roots; and yet ſo, that euery of thoſe three parts of the Tree or Plant, ſeuerally by themſelues, haue in them their peculiar <hi>Salt, Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercurie,</hi> without which they cannot conſiſt, how ſimple ſo euer they be. For whatſoeuer hath being within the whole compaſſe of Nature, it doth conſiſt of theſe three eſſences. And albeit ſome Trees and Plants are ſaid to be Mercuriall, ſome Sulphurus, and ſome Saltiſh, it commeth hereof becauſe the Mercuriall doe containe more Mercurie, the Sulphurus, more Sulphur: and the Saltiſh, more
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:181123:23"/>Salt in them then others. For ſome Trees are to be ſeene more full of Roſine, and Sulphurus matter than other ſome, as the Pyne, and Firre Trees, which are alwaies greene on the coldeſt mountaines, becauſe they abound with their Sulphurus beginning, the principall vitall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their growing. For there are ſome other plants, as the Laurell, the Trees of Orenges, Lymonds, and Cytrones, which continue long greene, and yet ſubiect to colde, becauſe their Sulphur is not ſo eaſely diſperſed, as is the Sulphur of the Firre Trees, which are Roſine, and are therefore of a threefold more conſtant life, furniſhed againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie of times. Furthermore, all ſpice Trees, and odoriferous hearbs are Sulphurus, and as there are ſundry ſorts of Trees of this kinde, ſo are there an infinite ſort of Sulphurs, whereof I cannot ſtand now to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate. The plants &amp; hearbs which more abound with Salt than others, are to be diſcerned by their taſte, ſuch are Celadine, Nettle, Aron, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh, Muſtard-ſeede, Porret, Leekes, Garlicke, Onions, Ramſons, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiccaria, and ſuch like, which alſo by the plenty of their Salt, doe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrue themſelues from the colde of Winter. As for other plants, aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with Mercurie, none are comparable to <hi>Roſa ſolis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Are thoſe three beginnings to be found in animals or liuing creatures, that haue ſenſe alſo, as they are in vegetable plants, and ſuch like?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I tolde you before that there is nothing in Nature, but it conſiſteth of theſe three: euen the very fowles of the Aire, and fiſhes that liue in the water, and wormes of the Earth. In the Egge, whereof the fowle taketh his beginning, theſe are ſeuerally to be ſeene, the white of the Egge ſheweth the Aethereall Mercurie, wherein is the ſeede, and the Aethereall ſpirit, the Author of generation, hauing in it the generating power, whereof the bird is chiefly procreated. The yolke of the Egge, which is the nouriſhment of the bird, is the true Sulphur. But the thinne skinne and the ſhell is altogether Salt. And this Salt is the moſt fixed and conſtant of all other Salts of Nature. So as the ſame being brought to blackneſſe, and then freed from the combuſtible Sulphur therein, by artificiall calculation, it will endure all force of fire, a property belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the moſt fixed Salts. This Salt duly prepared is very fit to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue the ſtone and to auoide it. As theſe three are in the Egge, ſo doe they paſſe into the bird: for Mercurie is in the bloud and fleſh, Sulphur in the fat, and Salt in the Ligamens, ſinewes, bones, and more ſolide parts, and the ſame beginnings are more airie and ſubtill in birds then in fiſhes and terreſtrials, as for example the oylely ſubſtance of birds which is the Sulphur, is alwaies of more thinne parts, than that of fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes or of beaſts. The ſame may be ſaid of fiſhes, which albeit they be procreated &amp; nouriſhed in the colde water, yet doe they not want their hot and burning fatneſſe. Alſo that there is in them Mercurie and Salt, no man well aduiſed will denie. All Terreſtriall liuing creatures
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:181123:23"/>doe conſiſt in like ſort of theſe three beginnings: but in a more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble degree of perfection they appeare in them, than in vegetable things. For the vegetables whereon the beaſts doe feede, being more crude, are concocted in them, and are turned into their ſubſtance, whereby they are made more perfect, and of greater efficacie. In vegetables there are onely the vegetatiues, but in beaſts, there is not onely the vegetating facultie, but alſo the ſenſitiue, and are therefore of a more noble and better nature. The Sulphur appeareth in them by their greaſe, tallowe, and by their vnctuous oylely marrow, and fatneſſe, apt to burne, their Salts are repreſented by their bones and more ſolide parts, euen as their Mercuries doe appeare in their bloud, and in the other humours and vaparous ſubſtances, all which ſingular parts, are not therefore called Mercurie, Sulphur, and Salt, without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of the three beginnings together, but in Mercurials, Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: in Sulphurus Sulphur: in the Saltiſh, Salt hath the greateſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Out of the which three beginnings of minerals, vegetables, and animals, diuers oyles, liquors, and Salts, apt for mans vſe, both to nouriſh, and alſo to heale and cure, may by <hi>Chymicall</hi> Art be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>For as much as Salt, Sulphur, and Mercurie, are the eſſences and beginnings of all things, I would gladly heare, after what manner man is compounded of them, who as he is the moſt excellent creature vnder the cope of Heauen, ſo me ſeemeth his compoſition ſhould be far more excellent than that of others.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>In man, as in a little world, are contained theſe three beginnings, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as different and manifold manner as they are in the great world, but more ſpirituous &amp; far better. For man is called a <hi>compendium</hi> of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter world. And therefore <hi>Gregory Nazianzene</hi> in the beginning of his booke concerning the making of man, ſaith: <hi>God therefore made man after all other things, that he might expreſſe in him, as in a ſmall table, all that he had made at large.</hi> For as the vniuerſall frame of this world is deuided into three parts, into <hi>Intellectuall, Elementarie,</hi> and <hi>Caeleſtiall,</hi> the meane be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene which, is the <hi>Caelestiall</hi> (which doth conioyne the other two, not onely moſt different, but alſo cleane contrary: that is to ſay, that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame intellectuall wholy formall and ſpirituall, and the Elementarie which is materiall and corporate) ſo in man the like triple world is to be conſidered, as lt is diſtributed into the parts, notwithſtanding moſt ſtrictly knit together and vnited: that is to ſay, the Head, the Breaſt and Belly, which is inferiour to the other two, &amp; comprehendeth thoſe parts which are appointed for generation and nouriſhment, correſpondent to the lower Elementarie world. The middle part which is the breaſt, where the heart is ſeated, the fountaine of the bodies motion, of life and of heate, reſemble that celeſtiall middle world, which is the beginning
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:181123:24"/>of life, of heate, and of all motion, wherein the ſonne hath the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence as the hart in the breaſt. But the higheſt &amp; ſupreame part, which is the head, wherein is the braine, containeth the originall of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and is the ſeat of treaſon, like vnto the ſupreame intellectuall world, which is the Angelicall world. For by this part man is made partaker of the celeſtiall nature, and of vnderſtanding, of the ſenſitiue and vegetating Soule, and of all the celeſtiall functions formall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible: whereas otherwiſe his Elementarie world is altogether groſſe, materiall, and terreſtriall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue obſerued one thing in your whole diſcourſe hitherto, that all the things in Nature, are comprehended in the number of three, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that triple proportion, wherein God is ſaid to haue made all things in waight,<note place="margin">Wiſedome. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> number, and meaſure: which muſt needes containe a great miſterie, which I pray you vnfold vnto me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>There is indeede a great miſterie in this point to be conſidered. For firſt the number of three repreſenteth the moſt holy and Diuine Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in vnitie. It is therefore a moſt holy and potent number, and the number of perfection. All dimenſion conſiſteth in three, in Longitude, Latitude, and Thickneſſe. All corporall and ſpirituall bodies conſiſt of three, of Beginning, Middle, and End. All meaſure of time is in the number of three, Paſt, Preſent, and to Come. All magnitude is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in three proportions in Line, Superficies, and Body. Harmonie containeth three Symphonies, <hi>Diapazon, Hemiolion,</hi> &amp; <hi>Diateſſaron.</hi> There are but three kindes of liuing creatures, Vegetatiue, Senſitiue, and Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuall. There are three quaternions of the celeſtiall ſignes, Fixed, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and Common. There are three faculties in man: Naturall, Vitall, and Rationall. And man exiſteth wholy in the number of three, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of Body, Soule, and Spirit. The Soule hath three principall facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Reaſon, Memorie, and Will. Therefore it is true which you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, that GOD in ſuch generall manner hath numbred the whole worke of his hands by the number of three, that no one thing can be ſhewed in vniuerſall Nature, which hath not this cognizance of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Trinitie in vnitie.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas you ſaid euen now, that man conſiſteth in the number of Three, to wit, of <hi>Body, Soule,</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> it is plaine that <hi>Soule</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> haue beene alwaies taken for one thing. I pray you therefore heare how they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:181123:24"/>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot otherwiſe diſtinguiſh them, then they are already diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed in the holy Scriptures: as in this place where the Author of the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes writeth thus. <hi>The word of God</hi> (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) <hi>is mightie in operation, and ſharper then any two edged ſword, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth through, euen to the deuiding aſunder of the Soule, and of the Spirit, of the ioynts, and of the marrow.</hi> And in another place hee ſaith: <hi>I pray God that your whole Spirit, Soule and Body</hi> (that is to ſay, the whole man which conſiſteth of theſe three) <hi>may be kept blameleſſe vnto the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Salomon</hi> alſo in his booke called <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> maketh a diſtinction betweene <hi>Soule</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> where he ſaith: <hi>And the Soule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vnto God that gaue it.</hi> But in another place ſpeaking of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Man and Beaſt haue all one ſpirit or breath.</hi> By which teſtimonies it appeareth, that <hi>Soule</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> are not one, but too diſtinct eſſences ioyned together in one body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Diuines commonly hold, that there is no difference betweene <hi>Soule</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> affirming that the Greeke words <hi>Pneuma,</hi> and <hi>Pſuchae,</hi> (that is, <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Soule</hi>) doe ſignifie one thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>If <hi>Pneuma,</hi> which ſignifieth but a breath, be the <hi>Soule,</hi> then muſt the <hi>Soule</hi> of man and beaſt be all one thing, which to thinke were too irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and groſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>If <hi>Soule</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> be not all one thing in eſſence, how commeth it to paſſe that in the ſcriptures they ſignifie ſometime the life of any thing, as here <hi>Anima mea eſt in manibus meis,</hi> my life is in my hands. Sometime <hi>anima</hi> ſignifieth the whole man: ſo 76. <hi>Soules</hi> deſcended with <hi>Iacob</hi> into Aegypt. Sometime for <hi>ſpirit</hi> or <hi>breath,</hi> as when <hi>Saul</hi> ſaid vnto the Amalechite, <hi>I pray thee come vpon me and ſlay me. Etiamſi anima adhuc in me eſt, becauſe my Soule is yet within me.</hi> And it was ſaid of <hi>Eutichus,</hi> which being a ſleepe at S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Sermon, fell downe as dead, <hi>Anima eius eſt in ipſo,</hi> his ſoule is yet in him, that is, there is yet breath in his body, that he may be reuiued againe. Alſo ſometime <hi>Anima</hi> is taken for nothing: ſo ſaid the Prophet, <hi>We haue conceiued and beene in trauaile, et peperimus Spiritum,</hi> and we haue brought forth a <hi>Soule.</hi> Finally, the <hi>Spirit</hi> is taken for the regenerated <hi>ſoule:</hi> ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Pneuma</hi> luſteth againſt the fleſh. And S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in diuers places calleth the <hi>ſoule</hi> by no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter name then <hi>Flatus,</hi> which ſignifieth no more then a breath or blaſt: <hi>Deus fecit</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>omnem flatum,</hi> God made euery blaſt; meaning euery <hi>ſoule.</hi> And it is written, <hi>God breathed into</hi> Adam <hi>the breath of life.</hi> Therefore theſe two words being thus confounded in the Scripture, how can you make them appeare to be two diſtinct eſſences?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>All that you haue alleadged, is nothing at all againſt the diſtinction
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:181123:25"/>of the eſſences of <hi>ſoule</hi> and <hi>ſpirit,</hi> albeit the one ſometime hath the name of the other. For admit, that the <hi>ſoule</hi> ſometime ſignifieth life and ſpirit, becauſe it is the principall ſpirit that giueth life, and is alſo immortall, yet doth it not therefore follow that the Aethereall ſpirit (which is tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie) ioyned therewith as a bond to keepe it in the body, is of the ſame eſſence. And where to ſerue your purpoſe you engliſh the word <hi>anima,</hi> to ſignifie ſpirit or breath, and againe, <hi>ſpirit</hi> to ſignifie <hi>ſoule,</hi> as in theſe places: <hi>Anima eius eſt in ipſo,</hi> there is yet breath in his body: and <hi>peperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ſpiritum,</hi> we haue brought forth a ſoule, you deale not faithfully in tranſlating, calling that <hi>ſpirit</hi> which is <hi>ſoule,</hi> and that <hi>ſoule</hi> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth <hi>ſpirit.</hi> It cannot be denied, but that ſo long as the <hi>ſoule</hi> is in the <hi>body,</hi> there remaineth alſo that breathing <hi>ſpirit</hi> with it, and no longer then breath tarrieth will the <hi>ſoule</hi> abide in the Heart and Braine: not becauſe they are all of one eſſence, but becauſe the <hi>ſpirit</hi> is a meane to conioyne the <hi>ſoule</hi> and <hi>body</hi> together for a time: according to the ſaying of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Thou takeſt away their ſpirit, or breath, and they die.</hi> This was the inſtrumentall <hi>ſpirit</hi> which God vſed in the conioyning of the reaſonable and immortall <hi>ſoule</hi> with <hi>Adams</hi> body, when hee is ſaid by <hi>Moſes,</hi> to breath it into him. And as for the place in the Galathians, <hi>The ſpirit luſteth againſt the fleſh,</hi> no man doubteth but that it is ſpoken of the regenerate ſoule, which is a more excellent eſſence then that by which man breatheth. What abſurdity I pray you can follow, if it be granted that the <hi>ſoule</hi> and <hi>ſpirit</hi> are two diſtinct eſſences? none in my iudgement: but being denied, many Atheiſticall and abſurd concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may be made againſt the immortality of the <hi>ſoule.</hi> Seeing therefore the word of God putteth difference in the denominations of either, I ſee no reaſon but that alſo the difference in eſſence may well ſtand. It is not denied but that the <hi>ſoule</hi> of man hath diuers denominations. For ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time it is called <hi>anima,</hi> becauſe it giueth life (as is already ſhewed) to the body, by a naturall vnion. For the <hi>ſoule</hi> is more excellent then the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> being alwaies one and like it ſelfe. It is ſometime called <hi>Animus Apo tou anemou,</hi> that is to ſay, of the winde or ſpirit, becauſe the moſt ſwift cogitation thereof is like in ſpeedy motion to the winde, reaching in a moment from Earth to Heauen: and ſometime it is called <hi>Mens</hi> of <hi>Mene,</hi> that is to ſay, of the <hi>Moone:</hi> becauſe mans minde is changed by courſe of time, as is the <hi>Moone,</hi> through his naturall imperfection.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Shew me I pray you the difference, which is betweene the ſoule and ſpirit of man, concerning ſubſtance and quality.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>The Soule of man is an immortall heate, moſt ſubtill mouing by it ſelfe, and the cauſe of the bodies motion. It is capable of Science, aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to a way like to it ſelfe, and to a ſubſtance of her owne affinitie, and leauing the terreſtrials, it ſeeketh to attaine that which is higheſt of all, partaking of the Heauenly Diuinity, often contemplating the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:181123:25"/>ſuper-celeſtiall place, and ſtandeth alone the moderatour of all things. To conclude, the <hi>ſoule</hi> of man is a ſimple, incorporate, and immortall ſubſtance, according to <hi>Galens</hi> opinion. But becauſe <hi>Hipocrates</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that he can finde no certaine opinion, vpon which hee may build concerning the ſubſtance of the Soule, <hi>Melius eſt de occultis dubitare, quam de incertis litigare.</hi> It is better to doubt concerning hidden things, then to contend about things vncertaine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I will not deſire to be wiſe beyond ſobriety, but will keepe my ſelfe within the limits of modeſtie: yet if it may ſtand with modeſt ſobriety, let me entreate you to ſay ſomewhat concerning the ſubſtance &amp; qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Spirit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Spirit naturall, is an Aethereall ſubſtance, differing from the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall body and humors thereof. <hi>Hipocrates</hi> calleth the ſame a ſtirring ſpirit, not for the thinneſſe and ſubtilty of the ſubſtance, but becauſe the ſame hath a great force and paſſage, as hath the winde. In regard that this ſpirit ſtirreth vp ſuch motions, it ſeemeth to haue affinity with the body, and in reſpect it cannot be ſeene, it may be thought to come neere to an incorporable ſubſtance, whereby it may be denied to be a meane betweene both to partake of either.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Thus then we muſt conclude, that man conſiſteth in the number of Three, that is to ſay, of <hi>Body, Soule,</hi> and <hi>Spirit;</hi> that the <hi>Spirit</hi> is as it were the chariot of the <hi>ſoule,</hi> the heate of this <hi>ſoule</hi> is celeſtiall and diuine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>It is true, I ſo hold and determine, till I can be better enformed: and I wiſh you not to make any doubt of this diſtinction, albeit as you haue before alleadged, that by ſome, <hi>ſoule</hi> and <hi>ſpirit</hi> are confounded &amp; made as one: and forget not this excellent ſentence of <hi>Iſiodore, Mens dum corpus viuificat, anima eſt: dum vult, animus eſt: dum ſpirat, ſpiritus eſt: dum recolit, memoria eſt: dum rectum iudicat, ratio eſt: dum aliquid ſentit, ſenſus eſt.</hi> That is, the mentall ſpirit when it quickneth the body, then it is the <hi>ſoule:</hi> when it willeth, then it is the mind: when it recordeth, it is memory: when it iudgeth right, then it is reaſon: when it doth breath, then it is <hi>ſpirit:</hi> when it feeleth by any of the fiue wits, then it is common ſenſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Let me yet a little further trouble you in recalling you to the place of <hi>Salomon,</hi> where it is ſaid thus. <hi>As the beaſt dieth, ſo alſo man dieth:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccle.</hi> 3.9.</note> 
                     <hi>for they haue all one breath or ſpirit, and there is no excellencie of the man aboue the beaſt, for all is vanity: who knoweth whether the ſpirit of man aſcend vpward, and the ſpirit of the beaſt deſcend downward to the earth?</hi> This place ſeemeth to import, that the ſoule of man is mortall, as is that of the beaſt, whereas you ſaid before, that the <hi>ſoule</hi> is a ſubſtance immortall, which I verely beleeue: yet I pray you open vnto me the meaning of <hi>Salomons</hi> words.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:181123:26"/>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>You muſt know that <hi>Salomon</hi> in thoſe words ſpeaketh not of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and vnderſtanding Soule which can neuer die, but liueth in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the felicity to come: which Soule S. <hi>Stephen</hi> yeeldeth and commendeth into the hands of God: which being ſo, is alſo free from all torment and paine: I ſay he ſpeaketh not of this Spirit, but of that Aierie ſpirit, which ſerueth to ioyne Soule and Body together, during this tranſitorie life. <hi>Salomon</hi> was not ignorant of the difference betweene theſe two Spirits: and therefore he ſpeaketh of two returnes anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to them both, and to their originals, namely, of the reaſonable Soule to God which gaue it: and the naturall Spirit which is common to man and beaſt alike, paſſeth to aire againe: but whether of them paſſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or downward, liuing and breathing in like mixture of aire, cannot be diſcerned by the externall and common ſenſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>This is a moſt wonderfull miſterie, that an eſſence, ſimple, incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, and immortall as is the ſoule, ſhould be knit to a compound bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: and that Nature, ſo farre vnlike, ſhould be brought to ſuch conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencie and familiarity, during their continuance together.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>It is indeede a wonderfull worke of God, that theſe three, <hi>body, ſoule,</hi> and <hi>ſpirit,</hi> ſhould be ſo conioyned in vnity, that the <hi>ſoule</hi> cannot ſeparate it ſelfe from the body when it liſt, nor keepe backe it ſelfe when the time is come to goe to the Creator. All paſſages are ſhut vp, when it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to abide, and all the parts are ſet open, when it is appointed to depart. And being departed out of the body, it liueth ſtill, not as it did in the corporall and tranſitorie body, which retained it by breath in the ayre, and by an equall mobility which is proper vnto it, being ſubtill, ſwift, and eternall. It ſeeth, heareth, and toucheth, and vſeth the reſt of the ſenſes after a more effectuall manner then afore, hauing an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence and iudgement, not imperfect and in part (as afore) but know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all things wholy and ſpiritually. Therefore becauſe it is a ſimple, pure, and vncompounded eſſence it cannot die. Hereupon <hi>Iuſtine Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir</hi> ſaith: the ſpirit neuer dieth, for death can but touch that part which is animated by the ſpirit: but the <hi>ſoule</hi> being the originall and fountaine of life, cannot die. For that which is animated is one thing, and the <hi>ſoule</hi> animating is another thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Doe you not know that in the Scriptures, <hi>the ſoules of the wicked are ſaid to die,</hi> and that there is often mention made of eternall death? how can this be, ſeeing the eſſence of both thoſe ſpirits as well of the one as of the other is alike immortall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Albeit in the Scriptures the <hi>ſoules</hi> of the reprobate are ſaid to die, it is not to be vnderſtood as touching the eſſence and quality of the <hi>ſoule,</hi>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:181123:26"/>but in regard of the miſerie thereof, being forſaken of God, and caſt out of his preſence, (in whom all happy and bleſſed life conſiſteth) is left to it ſelfe in deſperation and torments of Hell, where it liueth ſtill in eſſence and ſubſtance in vnſpeakeable miſerie and woe, which is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall liuing death, euer dying, and yet neuer dead, abiding for euer, and euer in that ſecond death with the Diuell and his infernall ſpirits, are you not wearie <hi>Philadelph</hi> of this long diſcourſe? We haue ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently according to the manner of Philoſophers debated of theſe things, and it is now time to take our dinner: if therefore you pleaſe to keepe me company, you ſhall be very welcome to my houſe, where in the after-noone we may haue further conference.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I thanke you, and doe gladly accept of your courteous offer: and the rather becauſe I deſire to be enformed further in ſome things, which depend vpon that which hath beene already in queſtion.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:181123:27"/>
            <head>THE AFTER-NOONES CONFERENCE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Riſtotle,</hi> beſide <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Forme</hi> (whereof hath beene already ſpoken) appointeth <hi>Heauen</hi> as a third principle to be the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creatour of theſe: but foraſmuch as there are diuers <hi>Heauens,</hi> I would gladly learne the diſtinctions of their motions, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ſeuerall Orbes. I pray you therefore deſcribe them vnto me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Aſtronomers, and ſome Diuines, doe deuide the naturall <hi>Heanens,</hi> which were made out of the more noble part of that Chaos or firſt matter, into the number of eleuen, euery one being placed in their ſeuerall degrees, one aboue another. Whereof the firſt is a fixed and immoueable <hi>Heauen,</hi> created the firſt day, and was then repleate with holy Angels. This <hi>Heauen</hi> is a body moſt ſubtill, the firſt foundation of the world, and the greateſt in quantity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> This <hi>Heauen</hi> (as ſaith <hi>Peter Lombard</hi>) is that which <hi>Beda</hi> and <hi>Strabo</hi> call <hi>Coelum Empyreum,</hi> that is to ſay, a fierie <hi>Heauen:</hi> not becauſe any thing is there burnt or conſumed, but becauſe of the fierie light, with the which the ſame is illuminated. And S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and <hi>Baſill</hi> are of the ſame opinion alſo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond <hi>Heauen</hi> is the firſt moueable, which maketh the daily motion from the Eaſt towards the Weſt, returning againe into the Eaſt in 24. houres regularly, that is, no ſwifter at one time, then at another,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:181123:27"/>without wearineſſe or paine. And by that motion, this Heauen earrieth with it all the inferiour Heauens. This motion is made vpon the poles of the world; and this Heauen hath in it no ſtarres.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third Heauen is alſo voide of Starres, and is carried about with a double motion. The firſt is, according to the motion of the firſt moueable: the ſecond is, his owne proper motion, from the Weſt towards the Eaſt, vpon his owne proper poles, in two hundred yeeres, one degree, and 28. minutes. This Heauen is called Chriſtaline, becauſe it is cleare and tranſparent. It is alſo of ſome called the waterie Heauen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth Heauen is called the Firmament, which is adorned with innumerable Starres. Theſe haue no motion by the motion of their Heauen. This Heauen hath a triple motion. The firſt is from the Eaſt toward the Weſt, according to the motion of the firſt moueable, vpon the poles of the world, and is finiſhed in the ſpace of a naturall day. The ſecond motion is contrary to the firſt, and is from the Weſt toward the Eaſt, according to the ſucceſſion of the ſignes; at the motion of the third Heauen in 200. yeeres, one degree and 28. minutes. The third motion is the trembling motion, by which the fourth Heauen is moued vpon two ſmall circles, whoſe poles are the heads of <hi>Libra</hi> and <hi>Aries,</hi> of the fift Sphaere: and the Semidiameter of their circles is foure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, 18. minutes, and 43. ſeconds. This motion is called comming and going.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fift Heauen, is that of <hi>Saturne,</hi> who moueth himſelfe in his cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, making reuolution once in 30. yeeres.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The ſixt Heauen is the Sphaere of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> who moueth about in 12. yeeres.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The ſeauenth Heauen, is the Sphaere of <hi>Mars,</hi> who ſignifieth his cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular motion once in 12. yeeres.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The eight Heauen, is the circle of the Sunne, who goeth about the earth once in a yeere.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> The ninth Heauen, is that of <hi>Venus,</hi> who maketh a reuolution once in 246. daies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> The tenth Heauen, is the Orbe of <hi>Mercurie,</hi> who moueth round about his circuit once in 330. daies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> The eleauenth, being the loweſt Heauen, is that of the <hi>Moone,</hi> who goeth about the earth once in 28. daies, making in this manner 12. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolutions in one yeere. Thus you may perceiue the ſeuerall motions of the Heauens in their ſeuerall degrees.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Shew me I pray you whether all theſe Heauens in generall, or one more eſpeciall, is the cauſe of the procreation of the inferiour earthie and naturall bodies?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nunqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nimis dicitur, quod nunqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſatis dicitur.</hi> There is neuer too much ſpoken, where the diſciple is not weary in hearing. Know therefore that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:181123:28"/>as the <hi>Heauen,</hi> which is called <hi>Primum mobile,</hi> is the firſt of all motions, which tendeth to place, from which all other latter and ſucceeding mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as procreation, alteration, growing, or augmentation, and periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or death, doe come euen ſo, that body which is carried about with a continuall motion and circuit, muſt needes be the cauſe of all bodies procreated. And it is a very ancient opinion of the Philoſophers, that the Sunne mouing Aſtrall influences, is of greateſt vertue and power, which being placed by God in the middeſt of <hi>Heauen,</hi> illumineth all things both aboue and alſo beneath it, and with his beames maketh the whole world fruitfull, euen to the very center of the ſame. For as the fountaine of life in mans body, is the center of his heart (where that ſecret vitall ſpirit is contained, from whence naturall heate doth ſpring, heating, illumining, and quickning the reſt of the members): euen ſo, the Sunne by his heate and light, doth naturally quicken all the parts of the world both ſuperiour and inferiour. For in regard of his heate it is called the <hi>Heart</hi> of the world, and in regard of his light, it is called the eye of the world. The Sunne is the moſt noble body of all things that are in the naturall Heauens, and in the earth, therefore in reſpect of the worthineſſe thereof, and vertuous power wherewith it is endued, next vnto God it is called the parent of all things, becauſe the ſeminarie and formall vertue of all things is ſecretly comprehended therein.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Then it ſeemeth that the Sunne by his continuall and yeerely courſe comming toward vs, doth promote and ſet forward the procreation of things, and going from vs, doth cauſe their decay and periſhing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>It is very true which you ſay: for it agreeth with <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termineth that the celeſtiall and mundane conuerſion, is the cauſe of thoſe things which are begotten, and which periſh. It is neceſſarie (ſaith he) that this whole world which compaſſeth the earth about, be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued with his ſuperiour conuerſions and motions, that the whole ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue thereof may be gouerned thereby. For that ought to be accounted the firſt cauſe, from whence all things haue the beginning of motion. And further (ſaith he) this cauſe is ſempiternall, neither hath it as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing place, any determined end, but is alwaies in the end. Alſo in his booke <hi>de mundo,</hi> hee calleth Heauen an Element, farre differing from thoſe foure knowne, and common Elements, which he affirmeth to be diuine and immortall, and free from deſtruction. But for as much as there is in the Heauens a double or two-folde reuolution, and conuerſion, the one which is the moſt ſwift mundane motion, which is finiſhed in the ſpace of 24. houres, and the other whereby the ſeauen inferiour Orbes are turned backward, by a contrary motion to that of the higher Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: the firſt of theſe two going alwaies forward after one manner in a conſtant courſe without change, cannot be the cauſe of life and death, things ſo contrary. But the latter carying about the wandring ſtarres, by
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:181123:28"/>the Zodiacke, when it bringeth them to the North, maketh the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Spring and life of things, but when it carieth theſe into the South, it bringeth the fall of the leafe, and the decay of things terreſtriall. By this perpetuall calculation of the Sunne and Starres, the Heauen is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the Earth, and the inferiour Elements doe ioyne with the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Whatſoeuer is moued, is moued of another. What then is the cauſe of the generall motion of the Heauens in their ſeuerall Orbes? Some haue thought that the celeſtiall bodies are moued of their proper formes. Some according to <hi>Platoes</hi> opinion, &amp; conſent of the Philoſophers, haue denied them to be liuing creatures, affirming that it is one of the greateſt ſhew-tokens of life, that thoſe celeſtiall bodies haue the principall cauſe of their motion in themſelues, and that they ſtand not in neede of an externall mouer. And for this cauſe not onely the moſt auncient Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dean Aſtrologers, but alſo the Chieftaines of the old Phiſiologie, as well Greekes, as Egyptians (as witneſſeth <hi>Plato</hi> in his <hi>Cratilo</hi> and <hi>Epinomides,</hi> and elſe-where) haue thought that the Caeleſtiall Orbes haue life and Soule, from whence motion proceedeth: and that the whole world is quickned by an vniuerſall Soule therein, which they imagined to be ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piternall. Yea, this opinion was ſo ſetled in the mindes of the <hi>Atheniens,</hi> that they condemned <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> of an irreligious conceit, becauſe hee durſt affirme the contrary. What ſay you to this? Doe you agree to this Philoſophie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I allow it not, for it muſt be granted that God alone is the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and chiefe cauſe of all motion, and therefore men illumined with a more cleare light of the knowledge of God, than the Philoſophers had, in ſtead of that imagined Soule of the world, vnderſtand a certaine cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated ſpirit, which moued vpon the waters in the firſt creation: which Spirit receiued power from God, to quicken, cheriſh, and conſerue all things in their kinde and order, vntill the determined end of the ſame. Therefore we may ſafely ſay, that neither Heauen, nor the Starres, are animated as bodies organicall, and for that cauſe cannot be meete habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacles for a Soule: but are rather bodies regular and vniforme, moued by a certaine naturall neceſſitie, according to the wiſedome of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty. For we know that God paſſeth the whole frame of the Earth, Sea, and Heauens, who fulfilleth all in all. And to preuent the great ruine thereof, he hath of his great goodneſſe and infinite wiſedome, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed that generall Nature, to defend and preſerue this great worke, by the vertue and moderation thereof. And that by the continuall and yeerely reuolution of the eight Heauen, and by the influences and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of the Starres, Planets, and Celeſtiall powers, all things might be well gouerned, and abide conſtant in their eſtate, vntill the predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time of their diſſolution. And yet in ſuch manner, that God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:181123:29"/>ſtill ordereth all things in theſe ſecondarie offices, according to his owne ſecret will and predeſtination.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Hereby it appeareth, that God being the firſt Mouer and cauſe of all motion, is himſelfe immoueable: becauſe if hee were changeable, then muſt he neceſſarily be moued of another: but of another he is not moued nor can be, for then could he not be the firſt mouer: becauſe that thing which ſhould moue him, muſt needes be before him: and alſo becauſe he not being immoueable, ſhould be moued of another: and ſo in the mouing and moued, there ſhould be no end, but a proceeding infinitely, which Philoſophie reiecteth. And if we ſhould imagine, that he is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of himſelfe, then muſt he be deuided into the part mouing of and by it ſelfe, and into the part moued by it ſelfe, and ſo by motion he ſhall be without forme. Which to thinke of the moſt high and chiefe ſimplicity, were too deteſtable and execrable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>God no doubt is altogether immutable, who without all queſtion as he is eternall and immenſurable, ſo alſo hee is moſt ſimple and moſt perfect. For this cauſe the eternity which is in God, taketh from him all temporall motion, becauſe he is all in all. And this immenſurable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe taketh from him motion in place, becauſe he is euery where: and his exceeding perfection and ſimplicity, taketh away motion to Forme, becauſe he needeth nothing being moſt fully complete. Therefore in no ſort God is ſubiect to change and motion, but ſtandeth ſtable for euer: of whoſe ſtability the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh thus: <hi>Thou changeſt them, and they ſhall be changed, but thou art one and the ſame for euer.</hi> And <hi>Boetius</hi> very notably ſpeaketh hereof thus. <hi>O quiperpetua mundum ratione guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas: terrarum caeli<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſator qui tempus ab aeuo ire iubes: ſtabiliſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> manens das cuncta moueri.</hi> O thou which by a perpetuall order, doeſt gouerne the world, the maker of Heauen and Earth, which commandeſt the times to proceede from the beginning, and which remaining ſtable thy ſelfe, doeſt giue motion to all things. God therefore in whom all things liue, moue, and haue their being, is the ſame which giueth formes to all things, that be in the created Heauens and in the Earth: he is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the middeſt, and the end of all things. If then the Diuine power and vertue paſſe through, and is effectuall in all things: by which the ſame exiſt, &amp; hath appointed the perpetuall beginnings, deuiding through all natures their ſeuerall kindes, and fulfilling them with their proper ſeeds, by which they receiue the ſpirit of life, will any man make doubt that there is any thing in Nature, which is not truly diuine and ſo called? Some ſay of olde, <hi>Deorum plena ſunt omnia,</hi> all things are full of Gods. It is then raſhneſſe, vtterly to take away without reaſon this excellencie of the Diuinitie, infuſed by God into all naturall things, which opinion hath beene receiued by the conſtant tradition of all the ancients, and it is more then madnes, to acknowledge that there is ſome Diuine thing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:181123:29"/>giuen to many things, and yet not to vouchſafe the ſame a Diuine name.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Let it be as you ſay, that there is ſome diuine thing in things Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, yet what manner of thing that Diuine thing is, I well vnderſtand not, neither can I coniecture.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Why can you not coniecture? ſeeing in a naturall body there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more excellent then a ſimple forme, and nothing afore it. And for as much as the reſidue which apperraineth to Matter, are inferiour to Forme, as vile and tranſitorie, it followeth, and you may eaſely perceiue that the ſimple forme of a thing, is that Diuine thing which is ſought after. And whatſoeuer doth repreſent and expreſſe the nature thereof, the ſame alſo is partaker in ſome meaſure of the Diuinitie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>But what force or ſtrength doe you ſuppoſe that ſimple Forme to be of things of nature: which I muſt attribute to the force and vertue of the mixture of Elements?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>If the Elements and their qualities haue certaine vertues and facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties proper vnto them, then muſt the vertues and faculties of the Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie be farre greater, which in a higher degree ſurmounteth all other in dignity and perfection. Alſo all the functions and workes of this ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Forme, may of vs eaſely be diſcerned and knowne. But how and from whence they proceede, and what is the ſubſtance of the effecting cauſe or faculty thereof, is as much hidden and vnknowne to vs, as is the eſſence of the Diuinitie. We ſee that the <hi>Magnes</hi> or Loadſtone hath in it an attractiue faculty to draw Iron to it: that the ſtone <hi>Aſtroites,</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth of it ſelfe, if a little quantity of vinegar be put to it. That the Eſtridge hath a power by ſwift concoction to digeſt Iron: that a Pidgeon by his heate digeſteth ſtones, which a Lyon whoſe heate is more vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cannot doe. That a little fiſh called <hi>Echeneis,</hi> otherwiſe <hi>Remora,</hi> is able to ſtay a ſhip againſt any violence of Oare or winde in full ſaile, that out of the aſhes of a Phaenix, another of the ſame kind ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created. That the Salamander ſhould be rather nouriſhed by fire, then conſumed. That the Camelion liuing by aire, ſhould turne himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euery colour which he ſeeth. That a Cockatrice in his eye ſhould haue power to ſlay a man. That a Viper or Scorpion ſhould kill a man with poyſon. That an Adder ſhould preuent the force of a charme, by ſtopping his eare. That the fiſh <hi>Ephemera</hi> ſhould die the very ſame day that it began to liue: of the which one daies Feauer beareth the name. That the feathers of an Eagle mixed with other feathers ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them. That the wilde and fierce Elephant at the ſight of a Ramme ſhould be made tame. That a Vine ſhould not proſper, growing neere to a Laurell Tree. That the Almond Tree being ſolitarie, beareth no
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:181123:30"/>fruit, but growing with other plants, is very fruitfull. That there ſhould be ſuch familiarity betweene the Oliue and the Mirtle Trees, that the branches of the Myrtle ſhould ſo friendly embrace the boughes of the Oliue, and both their rootes to ioyne together in one. That the ſtone <hi>Tyrrhemus</hi> being whole ſwimmeth: but broken ſinketh. That where the Glow worme creepeth in the night, no Adder will creepe by day. That Rheubarb ſhould haue power to ſeparate Choler: Agarick Flegme: and Epithimum, Melancholy. That Hemlocke and Hellebore ſhould be to a man peſtiferous: and yet that the Quaile ſhould be nouriſhed with Helebore and the Starling with Hemlocke. That the ſeuerall parts of a Hare ſhould haue diuers Formes &amp; faculties to heale diuers diſeaſes. As the lungs, thoſe that be ſhort winded: the bloud to break the ſtone in the bladder or reines of a man: the bone which is behinde the knee in the after legge, to cleanſe away ſand and grauell: the Mawe outwardly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to retaine and ſtay a conception, the haue to ſtanch bloud. Theſe and many moe ſuch like are hidden in the Cloſet of Nature, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted cauſes whereof no man is able to ſhew, nor comprehend by any certaine reaſon. Yet it is mans duty being ſet vpon the op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Stage of this world, to take a view of all the creatures of God to him knowne, to ſearch after ſuch hidden cauſes therein ſoberly, that he may magnifie the moſt omnipotent and wiſe Creatour of Nature.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou hauing ſpoken afore of the celeſtiall motions, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth that you ſay ſomewhat concerning Water motion. Therefore ſhew mee now I pray you, the cauſe of the Seas motion: wherein I haue obſerved a great diuerſity, ſomtime ebbing and ſomtime flowing: one while calme, and another while turbulent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>The Sea in generall hath three degrees of motion, the one calme and quiet continually: as in that <hi>Archipelagus,</hi> called <hi>Mare pacificum,</hi> and <hi>Mare delzur:</hi> which is ſeldome troubled with tempeſt, that M. <hi>Anthonie Pigafetta,</hi> ſometime Knight of the Rhodes, and one that did accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie <hi>Magelanus</hi> in his firſt voyage and enterie into this Sea, vpon the firſt diſcouery thereof, teſtifieth, that hee with his company ſailed therein 4000. leagues in the ſpace of three moneths and 20. daies. In all which time being without ſight of land, they had no misfortune of winde, nor of any other tempeſt.</p>
                  <p>Another degree of motion is in theſe parts of the Ocean, called the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:181123:30"/>Spaniſh Seas, which doe moue and ſwell with ſurging waues like moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, in ſuch wiſe that the top Maſt of one Ship going before another, cannot be ſeene of the follower, being as it were in a valley betweene two water hils. In theſe Seas, Ships cannot ſaile neere together, leaſt they fall foule one vpon another. Otherwiſe in theſe Seas, the paſſage is leſſe perillous then in the narrow Seas, for that the billowes &amp; waues of theſe goe whole and breake not, the Sea in that channell being ſo deepe, that a whole dry-fat of line may with a Lead be ſunke therein without finding any bottome.</p>
                  <p>A third degree of motion is in that part of the Ocean, commonly called the narrow Seas, which coaſteth Northward, vpon England, Scotland, and Ireland, and toward the South, vpon Fraunce &amp; Flanders, and ſo along the trade toward the the Eaſt, from the Weſt, theſe Seas are ſometime calme, &amp; ſometime by occaſion of tempeſt very rough &amp; tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent, for that the paſſage of the Sea in that channell is interrupted with rockes and ſands, to the great hazard of them that ſaile therein.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>But for ſo much as the Sea is euer in motion, either ebbing or flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhew me I pray you the cauſe of ſuch naturall and inter changeable motion, which keepeth time and tide twiſe in 24. houres, from Eaſt to Weſt, and from Weſt backe againe to the Eaſt, in the circumference of the whole Globe of the Earth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I finde in Writers ſuch variety of opinion concerning this motion, that I know not certainly what to determine to content you, yet to giue you the beſt ſatisfaction I can herein, you ſhall haue my conceite, which neuertheleſſe I ſubmit to the iudgement of the more learned in Natures Schoole. I ſuppoſe that there are two principall cauſes of the ebbing and flowing of the Sea. The one ſupernaturall: the other naturall. The ſupernaturall and diuine cauſe is God, who in the creation of all things by his ſpirit which he created (as witneſſeth <hi>Tertullian</hi>) was the inſpirer and animater of the whole vniuerſall: which Spirit ſerued the will of the Creatour, as an Inſtrument to giue ſuch motion to the Sea, as wee ſee it hath, appointing it bounds which it cannot paſſe without the will of the moſt mighty Commaunder. Another naturall cauſe beſide that created Spirit, whereof <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaketh (calling it the Spirit of God) <hi>Iob</hi> expreſſeth by the ſimilitude of Fire put vnder a Pot, ſaying: <hi>It is God which maketh the Sea to boyle like a Pot.</hi> Hereof I gather, that there is a naturall fire, of two ſorts. One in-ſet, contained in the Marine Salt: for the Sea generally is Salt, euen to the North. And Salt (as witneſſeth <hi>Plinie</hi>) yeeldeth the fatneſſe of oyle: and oyle by a certaine natiue heate is of property agreeing to fire. And <hi>Ioſephus Querſitanus,</hi> and <hi>Christoferus Pariſienſis</hi> affirme, that Salt is both animall and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getall, hauing life in it as the radicall Balſam of Nature, and to be the firſt mouing thing in the ſame, which maketh to grow and to multiply,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:181123:31"/>and therfore ſerueth for the generation of all things: ſo as with the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets and ancient Philoſophers, it may be ſaid, that <hi>Venus</hi> the mother &amp; firſt beginner of all generation, is begotten of the ſalt ſpume of the male. For which cauſe <hi>Venus</hi> was called by the Greekes <hi>Aligines,</hi> as affianced to the ſalt Sea. The other naturall Fire, the cauſe of the Sea flowing and ebbing, is forraine or externall. And this alſo is of two ſorts. One ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terraneall, which is as fire vnder a boyling pot. For the earth hath more fire in it, then hath water: which fire lieth hidden in ſtones till it be bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten out with ſteele. This ſubterraneall fire doth alſo cauſe the motion of the Sea, being of ſubſtance liquide, fluible, moueable, and altogether a paſſiue ſubiect to acting fire. And when it beginneth to runne any way, the precedent part therof, by reaſon of the continuation &amp; cleauing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, is thruſt forward by the follower, according to this ſentence, <hi>Vndam vnila ſequitur,</hi> one water followeth another. Thus the Sea paſſeth to and againe from one Gulph to another. For there are two Gulphes cauſed by two vaſt continents, the one comprehending all Aſia, Africa, and Europe, and that other America. Which two continents deuide the whole Sea into two parts of the world, oppoſite one to the other, Eaſt and Weſt. Theſe two Gulphes reſt at no time, but like as Sea monſters doe, they breath to and againe, vntill the one haue engorged the other ſo full, that it is compelled to pay vnto his lender backe againe that which is borrowed. And thus the Sea hauing a naturall impoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to ſtay it ſelfe in reſt, ſuffereth a certaine reciprocall motion into and out of it ſelfe, without intermiſſion: which motion <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> calleth <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantoſin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The other externall heate, cauſing the ebbing and flowing of the Sea, is that which proceedeth from the Moone, which <hi>Aueroes</hi> calleth the Lady and Miſtreſſe of the Sea, who by her beames and influences maketh the Sea hot, and by the ſame heate doth beget exhalations in it, wherewith when the Sea ſwelleth, it floweth to the ſhoare and Sea bankes, fulfilling the Hauens with Tide. And the ſame exhalations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diminiſhed and abated, the Sea againe ſetteth in it ſelfe. Therefore when by the Moones aſcention and approaching to the South, her light and heate is encreaſed, then doth ſhe make the waters to ſwell and flow. But when ſhe deſcendeth and enclineth to the Horizon, her heate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by little and little diminiſhed, the waters doe fall and abate. Thus all theſe cauſes working together, the Sea doth moue in waight, num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and meaſure, according to the ordinance of the Almighty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lewes Vertomannus,</hi> in his booke concerning Nauigation into Eaſt India, affirmeth, that the flouds there haue contrary courſes to thoſe of ours, concerning encreaſing and decreaſing. Becauſe there (ſaith he) they encreaſe in the wane of the Moone: but here with vs in the full.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>If the report of <hi>Vertomannus</hi> be true, then are all the times and ſeaſons
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:181123:31"/>by the motion of the Heauens in the Hemiſphaere, contrary vnto thoſe of ours in this Hemiſphaere, in ſuch wiſe, that as the people enhabiting there, are <hi>Antipodes</hi> vnto vs; ſo alſo with them it is Sommer, when Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with vs: and night with them when day with vs: and then no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile if it be there with them a full Sea, when the Moone is in the wane, and low water in the full Moone, contrarie to the flouds and ebbes here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Let it be as you ſay and ſuppoſe. Whereas you ſaid before that the Sea hath ſometime a turbulent and raging motion: what is the reaſon thereof?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>There are two cauſes of ſuch motion. One is certaine exhalations bred in the Sea, cauſing windes to breake forth from thence. And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time a multitude of dry exhalations drawne vp from the Earth into the aire, cauſing ſtormie windes, which breake the courſe of the Sea to the greatamazement of Marriners, and perill of Ships. Who yet are ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly taken in ſuch ſtormes, but that they haue fore-warnings thereof by certaine tokens precedent: as by the roaring of the Sea in a great calme: by the ſporting and playing of Dolphins and Porpoyſes aboue the waters: and by certaine viſible fires, called S. <hi>Helen,</hi> S. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> and S. <hi>Clare,</hi> which are wont to hang on the Maſtes of the Ships, dazeling the eyes of ſuch as are there. After which fires, and other ſhew tokens, there followeth vndoubtedly in very ſhort time, great and intollerable tempeſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>What fires are they which you ſo name and ſanctifie. Are they not Spirits?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>They are no ſpirits, but naturall things, proceeding of naturall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and are ingendred of certaine exhalations. Of theſe <hi>Hieronimus Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danus</hi> writeth after this manner. There are two manner of Fires ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of exhalations, whereof one is hurtfull, the other without hurt. That which is hurtfull is fire indeede, ingendred of euill and venomous vapours, which in continuance of time, take fire, as apt matters to be kindled. The other kinde is no true fire, but like the matter that is in ſuch olde putrified wood, as giueth the ſhining of fire, without the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and quality thereof. Of the true kinde of fire is the fire-ball, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called S. <hi>Helen,</hi> which is ſometime ſeene about the Maſts of Ships, being of ſuch fierie nature, that ſometime it melteth braſen veſſels, and is a token of drowning, for as much as this chaunceth onely in great tempeſts, for the vapour or exhalation whereof this fire is ingendred, connot be compact in forme of fire, but is of a groſſe vapour, and by a great power of winde put together, and is therefore a token of immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent perill. As on the contrary part, the like Fires, called in olde time,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:181123:32"/>
                     <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> and now named the two lights of S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas,</hi> which for the moſt part fall on the cables of the Ships, leaping from one to another, with a certaine flattering noiſe like birds, are a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of ſecurity and of the tempeſt ouerpaſſed. For they are but vapours cleauing to the Cables, which in ſucceſſe of time the fire paſſing from one to another, appeare in the ſimilitude of a light candle. They are a token of ſecurity, becauſe they are litle, not ſlow or groſſe, whereby they might all haue ioyned together in one, &amp; thereby haue beene the more malicious, and laſted longer: whereas being many and but little, they are the ſooner conſumed. Thus farre <hi>Cardanus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue not heard of theſe Sea-fires before. But I haue read of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine whirle-pooles, into the which what Ship ſo euer commeth, it is ſwallowed vp, and the fragments of the loſt Ship are ſeldome caſt vp againe. What is the reaſon of this whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le-pooles motion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue likewiſe read that in the Norwegian Sea, are three Ilands, namely, <hi>Lofoth, Langanes,</hi> and <hi>Vaſtrad.</hi> The Sea that runneth betweene theſe Ilands, is called <hi>Muſcoſtrom,</hi> which ſignifieth boyling. The Sea when it floweth here, is ſwallowed into certaine Gulphes or Caues, and is blowne out againe at the ebbe, with no leſſe violence then the ſtreames of riuers, which fall from the mountaines. The reaſon why they are ſwallowed vp, which chance to fall in with this or the like Sea, is the eddie water, which whirling round about with the violent fall of the Sea, which before was pent in with the Ilands, maketh a great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draught, which violently ſucketh and ſwalloweth ſodainly. This is the wonderfull power of Nature, paſſing the fabulous <hi>Sympleiades,</hi> and the fearefull <hi>Malea,</hi> with the dangerous places of <hi>Silla</hi> and <hi>Charibdis,</hi> and all other miracles that Nature hath wrought in any other Sea hitherto knowne vnto men.</p>
                  <p>Now friend <hi>Philadelph,</hi> to the end you may the better vnderſtand what hath beene ſpoken before concerning the motion of the celeſtiall Orbes; and alſo that you may plainly ſee as in a glaſſe, how the Region of Fire, and Aire, vnder the Moone, doe compaſſe about the Earth and Sea: as alſo for the better perceiuing of things to be ſpoken hereafter: behold this Mathematicall Figure following.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:181123:32"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>figure showing motion of celestial orbs</figDesc>
                     <p>This outtermoſt circle of this figure of all the Sphaeres (which is infinite) doth repreſent the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitacle of God, who was before all time and place.</p>
                     <p>Time and Place began when this created World began to be.</p>
                  </figure>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:181123:33"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or ſo much as the Earth and Sea, make but one globous body, vnited and combined together, I pray you deſcribe the forme thereof vnto me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>The globous body of the Earth, in compariſon of the Heauens circumference, is a very ſmall body, leſſe then the Sunne, and bigger then the Moone, extending it ſelfe within a ſmall diſtance of the fierie Region, and in that regard is a great body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Doth not this Earth, being a ſpungeous body, ſucke into it, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the Salt that is in the Sea? which if it doe ſo, in my opinion, it ſhould procure barrenneſſe to the Earth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue forgotten (it ſeemeth) what I ſaid before, where I ſhewed you that the Salt of the Sea containeth in it the radicall Balſam of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and being ſo, it is the cauſe of the generation, firſt of moſt preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pearles in the ſhels of fiſhes, and of Corall, ſpringing out of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels of hard ſtones and rockes, ſpreading forth branches like a Tree.</p>
                  <p>Salt is ſo farre from making the Earth barren, that it fructifieth the ſame, making it fat, and giuing it power to be fruitfull. Salt encreaſeth and giueth a vegetating and growing vertue with ſeede in euery terrene thing. For what other thing is it which maketh the Earth fat, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to paſſe that one graine multipheth into an hundred, but a certaine ſtercoration, and ſpreading of dung and vrine of men, and beaſts vpon the eatrh, which compaſt is full of Salt? What other thing openeth the earth, and maketh it to ſprout in the beginning of the ſpring time, after that the Sunne is exalted into the ſigne of <hi>Aries,</hi> (which ſigne is the fall of <hi>Saturne,</hi> and the houſe of <hi>Mars,</hi> ſignes altogether fierie) but the ſublimations and eleuations of the Spirit of Salt? This is that which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth heate and quickneth: which maketh to grow, and which ioyeth and decketh the fields and the medowes with graſſe and flowers, and which produceth that moſt ample and vniuerſall vigour and vertue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſeemeth then that the naturall Salt of the earth hath in it a vitall and nouriſhing heate, whereby not onely the Caues and hollow places, but alſo Springs of water are made warme; as that famous Spring which atiſeth in one of the fiue Ilands of <hi>Molucca,</hi> called <hi>Bachian:</hi> where the water iſſueth out hot in the beginning, but is very colde when it hath
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:181123:33"/>ſtood a while in another place. This water ſpringeth from the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, on the which the fragrant Cloue-trees doe grow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Such are thoſe ſulphurous Springs alſo which ariſe out of the Earth in the Citie of Bathe, which are ſo much the more hot, by how much the Winter in colde is more vehement. And this doth yet further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by this example, that the mountaines of Norway and Sweathen are fruitfull in mettals, in the which Siluer and Copper are concocted and molten in veines, which ſcarſly can be done in fierie fornaces.</p>
                  <p>In Iſeland alſo toward the Sea coaſt, are foure Springs of water, of moſt diuers and contrary nature. The firſt whereof, by reaſon of his perpetuall and feruent heate, ſodainly turneth all bodies that are caſt therein, into ſtones, reſeruing neuertheleſſe their firſt formes and ſhape. The ſecond is of intollerable coldneſſe. The third is ſweeter then ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and moſt pleaſant to quench thirſt. And the fourth is plaine poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, peſtilent, and deadly. But this is to be obſerued that in theſe ſprings, is ſuch aboundance of Brimſtone, that 1000. pound waight thereof is bought for the tenth part of a Ducket. For the truth of theſe things reade <hi>Ziglerus,</hi> in his booke of the <hi>North Regions.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>You tell of ſtrange things, and report matter of meruaile.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>But to make you meruaile more, the ſame <hi>Ziglerus</hi> reporteth that in Iſeland are three mountaines of a meruailous height, the tops wherof, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit they be couered with ſnow, yet are the neather parts of them of like nature to the mount Aetna, in the Iland of Cicilie, boyling with continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all flames of Fire, &amp; caſting forth Brimſtone. One of theſe mountaines is called <hi>Helga:</hi> the other <hi>Mons Crucis:</hi> and the third is named <hi>Hecla:</hi> whoſe flames, neither conſume Flaxe nor Towe (matters moſt apt to take fire) not yet are quenched with water: &amp; with like force as the ſhot of great artillarie is driuen forth by violence of fire, euen ſo by the commixion and repugnancie of fire, colde, and brimſtone, great ſtones are here caſt out into the ayre. The Inhabitants of the Iland doe thinke that in this mount <hi>Hecla,</hi> is the place where the euill ſoules of their people are tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented. Thus <hi>Philadelph</hi> you may ſee, that the Earth is not without a naturall Sulphur &amp; Salt, which Salt by heate cauſeth both motion and generation, not onely of Trees, Plants, Hearbs, and Flowers, with fruits of ſingular vertue and beauty, wherewith the Earth is garniſhed (ſeruing not onely for neceſſity, but alſo for pleaſure) but hath alſo in the bowels thereof many excellent natures, as Salts and Sulphurs, of ſundry ſorts, minerals, and mettals in ſuch plenty, that it may ſeeme a ſtore-houſe of infinite riches, ordained by God, for man, for whom hee prepared this habitacle before he created him. And albeit this Globouſe body of the earth is not Sphaericall, or perfectly round, yet it tendeth to Sphaericitie, being contracted by hils and dales in the parts thereof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:181123:34"/>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Seeing the Sea which is combined and ioyned with the Earth, hath motion, it ſeemeth to ſome that the Earth hath alſo perpetuall motion. And of this opinion is <hi>Nicholaus Cuſanus</hi> (as appeareth in his booke <hi>De docta ignorantia</hi>) and <hi>Copernicus</hi> accordeth with him, as is to be ſeene in his booke of <hi>Reuolutions:</hi> who for their purpoſe alleadge theſe reaſons. Firſt, that we ſhould rather attribute motion to the contained, then to the containing; to the thing placed, then to that which affordeth place. Secondly, that it is conceite and imagination which maketh vs thinke that the Heauens doe moue, rather then any truth of ſuch motion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede. For that the motion of the Earth cannot be perceiued, but by a certaine compariſon of the fixed. As for example, if a man perceiue not the ebbing and flowing of the water, being in a Ship at Sea, where he ſeeth no land-marks, how ſhall he perceiue that the Ship doth moue? After the ſame manner, a man being vpon the Earth, and ſeeing nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sunne, Moone, nor Starre, it ſeemeth vnto him that he is in a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter immoueable, and that all other things doe moue. Thirdly, that it is very vnlike, that the vaſt and huge compaſſe of the Heauens ſhould make reuolution once in 24. houres ſpace, rather then the Earth, being but as a pricke in compariſon thereof. Fourthly, that the wandring Starres be alwaies more neere to the Earth toward the euening (as when they are oppoſite to the Sunne, the Earth comming betweene them and the Sunne) and further from the Earth at Sunne ſetting, when they are hidden about the Sunne, at what time we haue the Sunne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them and the Earth. Whereby (ſaith <hi>Copernicus</hi>) it plainely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that we haue the Sunne for our fixed center, rather then the Earth. Fiftly, that it is a condition farre more noble and diuine to be immoueable, then to be mouing and vnſtable, which quality of motion and inſtability better agreeth with the Earth, then with the Heauens. Other reaſons are aleadged, which being of no great importance, for breuity I omit. Theſe may ſuffice being the more principall, by which they maintaine the motion of the Earth: which reaſons ſeeme to mee pregnant and inuincible.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Then it ſeemeth you will preferre nouelty before Antiquity. For <hi>Ptolome,</hi> that great Atlas of the world, and Prince of the Aſtronomers, with the more part of auncient Philoſophers, haue euer beene of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that the Heauens doe moue, and that the Earth is firmely fixed. Therefore I ſay vnto you with S. <hi>Auguſtine, Qui errantem laudat, errorem confirmat, et qui adulatur ad errorem allicit:</hi> that is, who ſo praiſeth him that erreth, confirmeth the errour, and hee which flattereth, allureth to error. It is ſaid of <hi>Ixion,</hi> that he tooke a cloud for <hi>Iuno:</hi> So, the more part of men embrace lyes for truth, falſhood for certainty, and ignorance for knowledge. Men haue laboured to draw out of the ſhallow Fordes of their owne braine, the deepe and vnſearchable miſteries of GOD.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:181123:34"/>
                     <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> a man of ſingular wit, notwithſtanding his great learning and knowledge in humane Sciences, attained not to the thouſand part in the knowledge of thoſe things which are laide vp in the Clofet of Nature. Yet hauing an inſatiable deſire thereto, at the laſt, becauſe he could not perceiue the reaſon why the Sea cauſed ſeauen Tides in one day, at the ſttraight of Nigront, he caſt himſelfe into the Sea, vttering theſe words, <hi>Quoniam Ariſtoteles mare capere non poteſt, capeat Ariſtotelem mare:</hi> that is, becauſe <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> cannot comprehend the Sea, let the Sea comprehend <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> A iuſt iudgement vpon man, when he ſeeketh to be wiſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God and his word.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, Man cannot finde out the worke that is done vnder the Sunne: Man laboureth to ſeeke it but cannot finde it. The Sciences inuented by mans wit, are more varying then the skinne of the Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion; more contrary then the Elements: more perillous then the Sea: more light then the windes: more intricate then a laborinth: and more obſcure then darkneſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>It is true which you ſay, yet haue you not anſwered the reaſons of <hi>Copernicus</hi> and <hi>Cuſanus,</hi> whoſe opinions are alſo confirmed by <hi>Heraclides, Ecphantes,</hi> and by <hi>Nicetus Syracuſanus,</hi> and ſome others.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>My digreſſion from your queſtion is not altogether impertinent and from the matter. But now I come to anſwere <hi>Cuſanus</hi> and <hi>Copernicus,</hi> with reaſons not taken out of humane Philoſophie, which (as I haue ſaid) is vncertaine, the greateſt Philoſophers diſagreeing among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, which cauſed in their Schooles diuers Sects, as the Scaeptickes, Pyrrhonickes, Academickes, Peripatetickes, Platoniſts, Stoickes, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures, Pythagorians, and others, who as in opinion, ſo alſo they differed in name. I ſay I will bring you no deceitfull Philoſophie, but that which is diuine and infallible, proceeding from the wiſedome and mouth of that great God, who is the Creatour of the Heauens and Earth, who onely is true, and euery mortall man a lyar. Heare therefore what the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> being diuinely inſpired ſpeaketh, concerning the motion of the Sunne in his Sphaere: <hi>He commeth forth</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as a Bridegroome out of his Tabernacle, and reioyceth as a mighty man to runne his courſe: his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out is from the end of the Heauen, and his circuit is to the end of the ſame, and nothing is hid from the heate thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the Sunne and Moone moued not in their Sphaeres, <hi>Ieſhua</hi> ſhould in vaine haue required of the Lord the ſtay of their motions, till he were auenged of his enemies, ſaying: Sunne ſtay thou in Gibeon, and thou Moone in the valley of Aialon. The which came to paſſe as a miracle, contrary to the courſe of Nature: and the Sunne abode, and the Moone ſtood ſtill, &amp;c. So that one day was ſo long as two naturall dayes at that time. It was alſo ſupernaturall and a miracle, that the Sunne contrarie to his naturall motion and courſe, was retrograde in his Sphaere, going
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:181123:35"/>backward ten degrees, as appeared by the ſhadow of <hi>Ahazes</hi> Dioll. But as touching the Earth, it hath no motion at all naturally as hath the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens. For, <hi>God</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>hath founded it vpon the Seas, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed it vpon the flouds, ſo that it ſhould neuer moue.</hi> The Earth acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally may haue ſome violent motion, when God is angry with man for ſinne, at which time, <hi>the Earth ſhall tremble and quake, and the foundations of the mountaines ſhall moue and ſhake.</hi> Let therefore theſe Diuine war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranties and euidences of ſacred Scripture ſuffice to confound mans vaine inuention, &amp; fond imagination concerning the ſtability of the Heauens, and motion of the Earth. And to make plaine the demonſtration vnto you, that the Heauens moue, and not the earth, I will ſet before you a memorable Modell and Patterne, repreſenting the motion of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens about the fixed earth made by Art in the immitation of Nature, by a Gentleman of Holland, named <hi>Cornelius Drebble,</hi> which inſtrument is perpetually in motion, without the meanes of Steele, Springs, &amp; waights.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I much deſire to ſee this ſtrange inuention. Therefore I pray thee good <hi>Theophraſt,</hi> ſet it here before me, and the vſe thereof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>It is not in my hands to ſhew, but in the cuſtody of king <hi>Iames,</hi> to whom it was preſented. But yet behold the deſcription therof here after fixed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>What vſe hath the Globe, marked with the letter A?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>It repreſenteth the Earth: and it containeth in the hollow body thereof diuers wheeles of braſſe, carried about with mouing, two poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters on each ſide of the Globe doe proportion and ſhew forth the times of dayes, moneths, and yeeres, like a perpetuall Almanacke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>But doth it alſo repreſent and ſet forth the motions of the Heauens?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſetteth forth theſe particulars of Celeſtiall motion. Firſt, the houres of the riſing and ſetting of the Sunne, from day to day continually. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, hereby is to be ſeene, what ſigne the Moon is in euery 24. houres. Thirdly, in what degree the Sunne is diſtant from the Moone. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how many degrees the Sunne and Moone are diſtant from vs euery houre of the day and night. Fiftly, in what ſigne of the Zodiacke, the Sunne is euery moneth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>What doth the circumference repreſent, which compaſſeth the Globe about, marked with this letter C?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>That circumference is a ring of Criſtall Glaſſe, which being hollow, hath in it water, repreſenting the Sea, which water riſeth and falleth, as doth the floud, and ebbe, twiſe in 24. houres, according to the courſe
<pb facs="tcp:181123:35"/>
                     <figure/>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:181123:36"/>of the tides in thoſe parts, where this Inſtrument ſhall be placed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is to be ſeene how the Tides keepe their courſe by day or by night.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>What meaneth the little Globe about the Ring of the glaſſe, ſigned with this letter B?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>That little Globe, as it carrieth the forme of a Moone creſſent, ſo it turneth about once in a moneth, ſetting forth the encreaſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the Moones brightneſſe, from the wane to the full, by turning round euery moneth in the yeere.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Can you yeeld me any reaſon to perſwade me concerning the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the perpetuity of this motion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue heard before that fire is the moſt actiue and powerfull Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the cauſe of all motion in nature. This was well knowne to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> by his practiſe in the vntwining of the Elements, and therefore to the effecting of this great worke, he extracted a fierie ſpirit, out of the minerell matter, ioyning the ſame with his proper Aire, which enclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Axcltree, being hollow, carrieth the wheeles, making a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall rotation or reuolution, except iſſue or vent be giuen to the Axel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, whereby that impriſoned ſpirit may get forth. I am bolde thus to conjecture, becauſe I did at ſundry times pry into the practiſe of this Gentleman, with whom I was very familiar. Moreouer, when as the King our Soueraigne, could hardly beleeue that this motion ſhould be perpetuall, except the miſterie were reuealed vnto him: this cunning <hi>Bezaleel,</hi> in ſecret manner diſcloſed to his Maieſtie the ſecret, whereupon he applauded the rare inuention. The fame hereof cauſed the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to entreate his moſt excellent Maieſtie to licence <hi>Cornelius Bezaleel</hi> to come to his Court, there to effect the like Inſtrument for him, ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto <hi>Cornelius</hi> a rich chame of gold.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>It becommeth not me to make queſtion concerning the certaintie of that, which ſo mighty Potentates out of the ſublimity of their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes haue approued, yet me thinketh that time and ruſt, which corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and weareth out all earthly things, may bring an end to this motion in few yeeres.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>To the end time may not weare theſe wheeles by their motion, you muſt know that they moue in ſuch ſlow meaſure, that they cannot weare, and the leſſe, for that they are not forced by any poyſe of waight. It is reported in the preface of <hi>Euclydes Elements</hi> by <hi>Iohn Dee,</hi> that he and <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rommus Cardanus</hi> ſaw an inſtrument of perpetuall motion, which was ſolde for 20. talents of gold, and after preſented to <hi>Charles</hi> the fift Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour: wherein was one wheele of ſuch inuiſible motion, that in 70.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:181123:36"/>yeeres onely his owne period ſhould be finiſhed. Such ſlow motion cannot weare the wheeles. And to the end ruſt may not cauſe decay, euery Engine belonging to this inſtrument, is double guilded with fine gold, which preſerueth from ruſt and corruption.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>This wonderfull demonſtration of Artificiall motion, immitating the motion celeſtiall, about the fixed earth, doth more preuaile with me to approue your reaſons before aleadged, concerning the mouing of the Heauens, and the ſtability of the Earth, then can <hi>Copernicus</hi> aſſertions, which concerne the motion of the Earth. I haue heard and read of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſtrange motions artificiall, as were the inuentions of <hi>Boetius,</hi> in whoſe commendation <hi>Caſſiodorus</hi> writeth thus: <hi>You know profound things and ſhew meruailes, by the diſpoſition of your Art, mettals doe lowe in ſundrie formes:</hi> Diomedes <hi>picture of braſſe, doth ſound a Trumpet loude: a braſen Serpent hiſſeth: birds artificiall, ſing ſweetly.</hi> Very ſtrange alſo was the mouing of the Images of <hi>Mercurie: The braſen head which ſeemed to ſpeake, made by</hi> Albertus Magnus: <hi>the Doue of wood, which the Mathematician</hi> Architas, <hi>did make to flie,</hi> as <hi>Agellius</hi> reporteth. <hi>Dedalus</hi> ſtrange Images, which <hi>Plato</hi> ſpeaketh of: <hi>Vulcans</hi> ſelfe-mouers, whereof <hi>Homer</hi> hath written: the Iron Fly, made at Noremberge, which being let out of the Artificers hands, did as it were flie about by the gueſts that were at the Table, and at the laſt, as though it were weary, returned to his Maiſters hand againe. In which Citie alſo an artificiall Eagle was ſo ordered to flie aloft in the ayre toward the Emperour comming thither, that it did accompany him a mighty way. Theſe were ingenious inuentions, but none of them are comparable to this perpetuall motion here deſcribed, which time by triall in ages to come, will much commend.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe great miſteries were attained by ſpending more oyle then wine: by taking more paines then following pleaſure.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas before in your diſcourſe, you haue ſhewed after what manner this inferiour world is gouerned by the ſuperiour, and alſo how all things that are procreated, receiue their forme from thence: now to aſcend vpward againe, I pray you declare vnto me in ſuch plaine ſort as you can, in what ſence and meaning <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> maketh one thing, which is the firſt of all, and mouing all, to be the cauſe of all their beings ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created. For if Heauen be the giuer of Forme to euery creature, what
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:181123:37"/>neede is there of ſuch an obſcure and tedious ſearch? And what will it auaile to ſhew the cauſes of things, from that moſt hidden originall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophrast.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was of opinion, that there are two worlds: one, which is this viſible, compound, and corporeate world: and the other an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporeate world, which we cannot ſee: wholy repleniſhed with Formes, ſimples, and free from all mixture, body, and dimenſion, the moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie and bleſſed houſe of God, and of all his Saints: the Archtipe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplar of this inferiour and tranſitorie world, which he briefly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth in theſe words. It is manifeſt, that without the compaſſe, and aboue the created Heauens there is neither place, emptineſſe, nor time. Wherefore thoſe things which be there, are neither apt to be in place, neither doth time cauſe them to be olde, neither is there mutation of any of them, which are ſet and placed aboue the vttermoſt conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, called <hi>Primum mobile.</hi> But being ſubiect to no tranſmutations, nor affections, doe enioy the beſt and moſt ſufficient life in the vniuerſall eternity. And their beſt life is contemplation, then the which there can be nothing more ſweet, and delectable. Vpon theſe words of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> I conclude, that from this one thing cometh all things procreated, as is ſhewed you before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>What manner thing is that eternitie, wherein the Saints of God haue life?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>It is an euerlaſting being, or (if you pleaſe) you may call it a <hi>Sempi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie,</hi> which in very deede is God. For by that name <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaid, he knew God, as theſe words of his declare; <hi>In Deo vita nimirum aeuam<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> continuum at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> perpetuum ineſt, hoc enim ipſe eſt Deus:</hi> That is God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is life and a continuall and euerlaſting being. And leaſt it might ſeeme nouelty, and an abſurd thing to attribute this name vnto God, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, that this name was diuinely giuen by the Auncients. For as the end which comprehendeth the time of the lfe of euery thing, is called age, and a long laſting time: ſo the end of the vniuerſall created Heauens, and the end which containeth the whole infinite time, is an euerlaſting being and eternitie, for it is immortall and diuine. And how infinite Gods knowledge of all things is, it hereby appeareth, that Gods whole life is a working of the minde: for God is his owne act, and that act which is by it ſelfe, is his beſt and perpetuall life. If the action of the minde (which is a contemplation) be the perpetuall life of God, who then will make any queſtion, but that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> attributed the knowledge of all things vnto God? For he verely is the knowledge of all things, his owne action, and his owne life, whom <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrateth to be the moſt chiefe and ſuper-excellent God, to be perpetuall, perfect, immoueable, indiuiſible, that cannot be defined by greatneſſe, nor by parts ſubiect to no alteration nor affection, as to whom nothing
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:181123:37"/>is in any ſort contrary. And at the laſt he concludeth this demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe things vpon this reaſon: namely, that in motions it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, that at the laſt we come to ſomething which moueth and is not moued, which ſelfe and ſame is perpetuall, and both ſubſtance and act alſo. And he is the very ſame whom before he called the firſt of all things, mouing all things. Whatſoeuer Mindes and Formes are aboue the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, Citizens of that Olimpicke habitacle, if they haue not the ſame forme that God hath, yet haue they ſuch a condition, ſtate, and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as is next vnto it in degree.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>What degree and dignitie is that which theſe heauenly Citizens enioy?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>It is the ſtate of perfect bleſſedneſſe, and the fruition of true felicitie in the life to come.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>But the Philoſophers were of opinion that the chiefe good and feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, conſiſted in the good things of this life: as in ſtrength, health, beautie, pleaſure, and ſuch other good things of the body. Alſo in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, in fortitude, conſtancie, patience, temperance, wiſedome, and other vertues, and good things of the Minde: finally, in libertie, riches, honours, friends, and in ſuch like goods of Fortune. And it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me, that this is a happy man which is bleſſed with theſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>The Heathen Philoſophers which had not the knowledge of God by his word, could not define any thing certaine concerning true feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie: in ſo much that Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, that there are reckoned vp 288. opinions concerning felicitie. Wherefore reiecting the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men, let vs that haue a greater light of knowledge, know and be aſſured, that true felicity cannot ſtand in the vaine and tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie things of this life: whereof <hi>Solon</hi> (one of the greateſt wiſe men of Greece) ſaid to <hi>Craeſus,</hi> when he boaſted of his ſubſtance, riches, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and power of his Kingdome, theſe words: No man is happy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death. Whereby he did put him in minde, that all theſe things were caſuall, and ſubiect to change, and might eaſely be taken from him, and he caſt downe into greater calamity. Wherein <hi>Solon</hi> was not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. For <hi>Craeſus,</hi> being ouercome by <hi>Cyrus,</hi> ſaw all that he had quite ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne: So in like manner, who but <hi>Marius</hi> for a time in Rome? but ſoone was he deiected, and <hi>Sylla</hi> got the fame. <hi>Sylla</hi> ſtood not long, but <hi>Pompey</hi> had the honour: and ſoone after <hi>Caeſar. Lucianus</hi> by a notable Epigram repreſenteth this, in ſetting before vs a territorie or plot of ground, which one while belonged to <hi>Archimenides,</hi> another while to <hi>Menippus,</hi> and after that by courſe of Fortune to others. <hi>Valerius</hi> the Emperour being captiue to <hi>Saporus</hi> King of Perſia, was conſtrained to ſerue in ſtead of a mounting blocke, ſo often as <hi>Saporus</hi> tooke his horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:181123:38"/>
                     <hi>I haue ſeene</hi> (ſaith <hi>Sirach</hi>) <hi>ſeruants on horſebacke,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccle.</hi> 10.7.</note> 
                     <hi>and Princes walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as ſeruants on the ground. Senacharth, Holofernes, Sampſon, Salomon,</hi> and many moe, had their dayes of proſperity and pleaſure, which ſoone came to an end. A day is but a ſhort time, ſuch is the continuance of mans pompe.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 5.27.</note> 
                     <hi>Giheſi</hi> is in health and cleane to day, to morrow a foule Leaper. The rich Glutton is ſecure to day, but at night leaueth life and all. It is not alwaies day with vs, the night of affliction muſt come vpon the Sonnes of men. Conſider the moſt flouriſhing Citie that haue beene in the world, Babilon, Niniuie, Troy, Hieruſalem, and others moe, and behold, they haue vndergone alteration and change: and ſome of them haue beene vtterly raced, and made a heape of ſtones. <hi>Nunc ſeges</hi> (ſaith <hi>Virgil</hi>) <hi>vbi Treia fuit.</hi> But what ſhould I ſtand to ſpeake of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration and ruine of Cities, when as whole Monarchies haue beene turned vpſide downe. The firſt Commaunders of the world were the Aſſirians; they being vanquiſhed, the Babilonians and Medes were Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narches: both theſe ſubdued, the Perſians were Emperours: after the Perſians, came the Macedonians: and at laſt the Romanes. True there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is which <hi>Tacitus</hi> hath vttered, in theſe words. <hi>Quae nunc vetuſtiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma creduntur noua fuerunt: et quod hodie exemplis tuemur, inter exempla fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turum eſt:</hi> Thoſe things which are beleeued to be moſt auncient, were new: and it will come to paſſe hereafter, that the thing which wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend at this day with examples, ſhall be an example it ſelfe. But that which is more then all that hath bin ſpoken, the whole earth in the firſt world, garniſhed with the plenty of all creatures, was ſubiect to altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and was ouer-whelmed with <hi>Noahs</hi> floud, whereby it was made ſo naked, that the Doue found not where to reſt the ſole of her foot.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>If felicitie doth not conſiſt in any thing appertaining to this life, wherein then doth it conſiſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt, it conſiſteth in the true knowledge of God, and of his eternall Sonne Chriſt Ieſus: for this is eternall life (ſaith our Sauiour) that men know thee the onely very God, and whom thou haſt ſent Ieſus Chriſt. Vpon which words S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writeth thus: <hi>Infoelix qui omnia nouit, et te neſcit,</hi> Vnhappie is that man which knoweth all things, and knoweth not thee. And the Pſalmiſt pronounceth them bleſſed, which out of the knowledge of God bring forth holineſſe of life, ſaying: <hi>Bleſſed are they which are vndefiled in the way.</hi> Vpon which words alſo <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> ſaith: <hi>I know what thou wouldeſt haue, thou ſeekeſt for bleſſedneſſe: if therefore thou wilt be bleſſed, be thou immaculate.</hi> Bleſſedneſſe alſo conſiſteth in the free grace and mercy of God, in not imputing to vs our ſinnes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this ſentence: <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiuen, and whoſe ſinnes are couered: Bleſſed is that man to whom the Lord imputeth no ſinne.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23.</note> For, <hi>all haue ſinned, and are by nature the children of wrath: but are iuſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:181123:38"/>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>Then it ſeemeth that this is a good euidence of a Chriſtian mans fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie, if he know God aright, and liue in holineſſe of life, according to the commaundements of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>A true Chriſtian, hath beſides theſe a further aſſurance of his bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and felicity: for that he hath already in this tranſitory life, the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of true fel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ity in Chriſt, by a certaine participation. For, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>By hope we are ſaued.</hi> So that euen now alreadie wee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy tranquilitie of conſcience.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.24.</note> For we are aſſured that <hi>there is no damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to thoſe that are in Chriſt Ieſus, which walke not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit.</hi> Moreouer, whereas afore our reconciliation through Chriſt, we were as enemies vnto God, &amp; moſt hatefull vnto him: now through faith in Chriſt and our free iuſtification, we are at peace with God. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo being regenerate by the holy Ghoſt, we are endued with excellent vertues, eſpecially with brotherly charitie, then the which there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more excellent in the world.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.24. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6.</note> Thus walking in holineſſe of life (as did <hi>Henoch</hi> with God) we by our good workes doe make our election ſure to our owne conſcience, the ſpirit of God teſtifying to our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſpirit, that we are the Sonnes of God, whereby we haue bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to call him Father: he that carrieth the picture of a man in his hand, may be ſaid to haue in his hand a man, albeit there is no ſuch Eſſence: So man may be ſaid to haue here alreadie the fruition of eternall life, becauſe they apprehend it by faith, and liue in expectation thereof, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying in their mindes the Image of eternitie.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.</note> 
                     <hi>I liue</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>by the faith in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>But the tribulations and afflictions which Gods children doe ſuffer in this life, is a ſore temptation, and many times ſhaketh their faith, and daunteth their ſpirit, ſo that in ſtead of happineſſe here, they may account themſelues miſerable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>The tribulations and afflictions which Gods children doe ſuffer in this life, maketh them not miſerable, becauſe by them as by a way,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 14.22.</note> they enter into the Kingdome of Heauen. The Saints and children of God doe moſt gloriouſly ſhine in tribulation, whereby alſo they are aſſured of Gods loue. For they know that if they be not vnder chaſtiſement, whereof all Gods children are partakers, they are baſtards &amp; not ſonnes: therefore tribulation worketh in them patience: patience, experience:<note place="margin">Heb. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note> experience, hope: and hope maketh not aſhamed. This maketh them to ſay confidently with the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Who ſhall ſeparate me from the loue of God in Chriſt? ſhall tribulation, or anguiſh, or perſecution, or famine, or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, or perill, or ſword?</hi> and ſo forth.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35.</note> 
                     <hi>I am perſwaded</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:181123:39"/>be able to ſeparate vs from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</hi> For all things proceede happily, to them that loue God. And this is an eſpeciall comfort to them, that their afflictions ſhall not be perpetuall, as ſhall be thoſe of the wicked, whoſe rod ſhall not come into the lot of the righteous:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.3.</note> for affliction ſhall deſtroy the wicked: <hi>Moab ſhall be threſhed as ſtrawe.</hi> To a worldly and carnall minde, which looketh vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on nothing but vpon the proſperitie of the wicked, affliction ſeemeth vnfit for Gods children, and therefore repining at their miſerie, haue ſaid: <hi>Doe they that dwell at Babilon any better that they ſhould haue the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of Sion? Thou ſuffereſt them that ſinne, and deſtroyest thy owne people.</hi> But wee muſt haue an eye to the wiſedome of God herein, who hath made the way to celeſtiall felicitie very hard and vnpleaſant, leaſt men being detained with the pleaſures of this life, ſhould be ſtayed from their heauenly courſe, and therefore hee ſendeth vpon them tribulation, to make them more ſpeedily to come vnto him. For thus he dealt with his olde people, the children of Iſrael, laying on their backes the great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction vnder <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that they might the more earneſtly deſire the land of promiſe: before <hi>Abraham</hi> had a ſetled reſt, he liued a Pilgrimes life: before <hi>Dauid</hi> enioyed the Kingdome, he was a long time perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Saul:</hi> before <hi>Iacob</hi> was enriched, he was in ſeruitude to <hi>Laban</hi> 14. yeeres: before <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had the rule in Egipt, he was caſt into priſon: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Iſraelites came into the land of Promiſe, they wandred fortie yeeres in the Wilderneſſe. Thus you may ſee the good end of affliction, which is like vnto <hi>Aarons</hi> rod, being rightly vſed, it is Gods rod ſent for our good: but if it be caſt vnder foote and deſpiſed, it will be a ſerpent, and ſting vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>In what points doth the felicitie to come conſiſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
                  <p>The true felicitie of that Heauenly and moſt bleſſed life to come, conſiſteth in theſe things. Firſt, in the reſtoring of all the chiefe things in Nature to a farre greater, and more high perfection then now they haue,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom</hi> 8.19.</note> of the which S. <hi>Paul</hi> writeth thus. <hi>The feruent deſire of the creature waiteth, when the ſonnes of God ſhall be reuealed. Becauſe the creature is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto vanitie, not of it owne will, but by reaſon of him that hath ſubdued it vnder hope. Becauſe the creature ſhall be deliuered from the bondage of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption into the glorious libertie of the Sonnes of God. For we know that euery creaure groaneth with vs alſo, and trauaileth in paine together vnto this preſent.</hi> Alſo in his Epiſtles to the Epheſians, and Coloſſians, he ſaith: <hi>that all things whether in Heauen or in Earth, ſhall be reſtored in Chriſt.</hi> And the Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7.</note> ſpeaking of the ſame reſtoring, writeth thus: <note place="margin">Verſe. 10.</note>
                     <hi>The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens and Earth which are now, are kept by the ſame word in ſtore, and reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vnto fire, againſt the day of iudgement.</hi> And afterward, he ſaith: <hi>
                        <note place="margin">Verſe. 13.</note>The Heauens ſhall paſſe away with a noiſe, and the Elements ſhall melt with heate, and the earth, with the workes that are therein, ſhall be brent, and being on fire
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:181123:39"/>ſhall be diſſolued. But we looke for new Heauens, and a new earth, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſſe.</hi> By which words I gather, that when Chriſt our Lord ſhall come to iudgement, in the laſt period of time, the foure Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (whereof all creatures conſiſt) hauing in them matter both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtible, and incombuſtible, as the Heauen, ſhall by the wonderfull po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God, be changed. For the combuſtible hauing in it a corrupt and droſſie matter, which maketh them ſubiect to corruption, ſhall in that great and generall refining day be purged through fire, and then God will make new Heauens and a new Earth, &amp; bring all things to a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaline cleareneſſe, and will make the foure Elements perfect, ſimple, and fixed in themſelues, that all things may be brought to a Quinteſſence of eternitie: So that the world, as touching the Nature thereof, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſhall not periſh, but be made new, to a greater perfection then now it hath. In regard whereof, S. <hi>Iohn</hi> compareth it to a Citie, which is made of pure golde, with a great and high wall of the precious ſtone called <hi>Iaſpis:</hi> the wall whereof had alſo twelue foundations, made of 12. precious ſtones. Alſo 12. gates, made of 12. rich ſtones, called <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites,</hi> and euery gate was an entire <hi>Margarit:</hi> The ſtreetes of the Citie were paued with gold, enterlaide alſo with pearles and precious ſtones. The light of the Citie was the cleareneſſe and ſhining of Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſitting in the middeſt thereof: from whoſe ſeat proceeded a riuer of water, as cleare as Chriſtall, to refreſh the Citie, and on both ſides of the bankes, there grew the Tree of life, giuing out continuall fruit. There was no night in that Citie, nor any defiled thing entered there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but they (ſaith he) that are within, ſhall liue for euer and euer. By this deſcription S. <hi>Iohn</hi> giueth vs to vnderſtand, that ſo great is the feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie prepared for vs in the Kingdome of Heauen,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> that the eye hath not ſeene, neither the eare heard, nor the heart of man conceiued what things God hath prepared for thoſe that loue him.<note place="margin">Apoc. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> The Kingdome and Citie, ſhall in ampleneſſe and beautie be farre beyond the reach of mans reaſon to comprehend. Yet the ample greatneſſe may partly be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the view of the ſtarres. For if the leaſt of them be of ſuch great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as all the Princes of the world haue not within their power, ſo much compaſſe and ſpace, and yet an innumerable multitude of ſtarres, haue place in the firmament, where there remaineth ſtill roome &amp; ſpace for many moe: how great then is the ampleneſſe and capaſitie of the Heauen it ſelfe? Verely, we may ſay with <hi>Baruch: O Iſrael,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Baru.</hi> 3.24.</note> 
                     <hi>how great is the houſe of God, and how large is the place of his poſſeſſion?</hi> Another point beſide the greatneſſe of the place where we ſhall dwell for euer, which will encreaſe our happineſſe, is, that in the ſame there ſhall be no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of euill that may bring to Gods children, ſorrow, paine, or annoy, ſo as it ſhal be verified which is ſaid in the Pſalme: <hi>There ſhall no euill hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vnto thee, neither ſhall any plague come nigh thy dwelling:</hi> In this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes, and there ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrow, neither crying, neither ſhall there be any more paine:
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:181123:40"/>for the firſt things are paſſed.</hi> A third point which ſhall encreaſe our feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, will be the exceeding reſplendant glory of the glorified bodies, and creatures in that Kingdome. For if one Angell is much more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, then all that we can now ſee with our bodily eyes: what a thing will it be, and how glorious a ſight, to behold the whole hoaſt of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, with their bleſſedneſſe, beſide the diuine Maieſtie and glory of our God? whoſe glory ſhall make vs to ſhine as the Sunne in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of our Father. And then hauing ſuch glorified bodies after their owne likeneſſe, we ſhall ſee God as he is, and behold him face to face. And therefore S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith: This onely ſight of God is our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe; and therefore it is onely promiſed to the pure in heart. O what a ioy ſhall it be, when at one view we behold the moſt high and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Trinitie, and all miſteries whatſoeuer are in God! for what ſhall not he ſee, who ſeeth him that ſeeth all things? Then ſhall mans minde haue perpetuall reſt and peace, neither ſhall it deſire any further vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, when hee hath all before his eyes, that may be vnderſtoode. Then ſhall mans minde be quiet, when he enioyeth that felicitie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all other things, as in a fountaine and Ocean of all happineſſe, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. Then ſhall faith haue her perfect worke: Hope ſhall enioy that which ſhe long deſired, but Charitie ſhall abide for euer. Then ſhall be ſung continuall praiſes vnto the Lambe, and the ſong although it be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſung, yet it ſhall be euer new.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>O happy and ſweet death, which deliuereth the ſoule from this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full body, as from a wretched and miſerable priſon, to dwell with Chriſt in Heauen,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23.</note> which Heauenly meditation moued S. <hi>Paul</hi> to deſire to be diſſolued, and to be with Chriſt. For vpon this diſſolution it cannot be expreſſed what ioy and pleaſure the Soules of the bleſſed ſhall haue, eſpecially when ſoule &amp; body ſhall be vnited againe in the reſurrection. O ioy aboue all ioyes, ſurmounting all ioyes, and without which there is no ioy. When ſhall I enter into thee (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>) when ſhall I enioy thee, to ſee my God that dwelleth in thee! O euerlaſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome! O Kingdome of all eternities! O light without end! O peace of God that paſſeth all vnderſtanding, in which the ſoules of the Saints doe reſt with thee, and euerlaſting ioy is vpon their heads, they poſſeſſe ioy and gladneſſe, and all paine and ſorrow is fled from them. O how glorious a Kingdome is thine, O Lord, wherein all the Saints doe raigne with thee, adorned with light, as with apparrell, and hauing crownes of precious ſtones vpon their heads? O Kingdome of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting bliſſe, where thou O Lord, the hope all Saints art, and the diademe of perpetuall glory, reioycing them on euery ſide with thy bleſſed ſight. In this Kingdome of thine there is infinite ioy, and mirth without ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: health without ſorrow: life without labour: light without dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: felicitie without ceaſing, and all goodneſſe without any euill. Where youth flouriſheth, that neuer waxeth olde, life that knoweth no
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:181123:40"/>end, beautie that neuer fadeth, loue that neuer vaniſheth, health that neuer diminiſheth, ioy that neuer endeth. Where ſorrow is neuer felt, complaint neuer heard, matter of ſadneſſe is neuer ſeene, nor euill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe is euer feared: becauſe they poſſeſſe thee O Lord, which art the perfection of their felicitie.</p>
                  <p>This ſweet and Heauenly meditation of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> if men would print it in their mindes, would very much further them to the ſeeking of eternall felicitie. Where is the zeale and loue of our Fathers become, who for the feruent deſire they had to enioy the felicity of the Heauenly Kingdome, liued continually in ſtraightneſſe of life, fared hardly, prayed continually, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atched carefully, and mortified their fleſh, humbled in ſack-cloath and aſhes in teares? Mans life in this world, is like a race, and compared to a warfaring life, wherein there muſt be running, and fighting, and violent motion, to get the crowne and triumph. So did S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith: <hi>I haue fought a good fight, and haue finiſhed my courſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.</note> 
                     <hi>I haue kept the faith, from hence-forth is laide vp for me the crowne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, which the Lord, the righteous Iudge ſhall giue me at that day: and not to me onely, but vnto all them alſo that loue his comming.</hi> Fighting &amp; running are violent actions, and motions to preuaile in our purpoſe and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe: So in this ſpirituall conflict which men are to vndergoe, againſt the impediments which may hinder them in their courſe to true felicity, (as are riches, honours, pleaſures, and worldly proſperity) there muſt be a violent wraſtling and ſtriuing. Men that haue beene a long time exerciſed in worldly affaires onely, and haue followed carnall delights with full ſaile, can hardly be reclaimed, to runne in the ſpirituall race, without a certaine violent ſtriuing againſt their affections,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 11.1.</note> whereby they doe as it were by violence plucke vnto them the Kingdome of God: for cuſtome breedeth a certaine Nature, and to alter Nature great vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence is required. Therefore they that in the ſpirituall conflict, intend to conquer the world, the Diuell, and the fleſh, muſt ſtriue to haue the Kingdome of God come vnto them, by the mighty power of the Spirit, (by whom they are armed) before they can attaine to it. For God then raigneth, and ruleth in man, when man pulleth vnto him by faith and loue the Kingdome of God. And thus the Kingdome of God is ſaid to be within vs.</p>
                  <p>O that men would ſeriouſly conſider theſe things, then would they not labour ſo earneſtly for things of no moment, for the tranſitorie things which are meere vanity, but would rather ſtriue with might and maine, to attaine to that moſt happy and bleſſed life, wherein all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and felicitie conſiſteth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thebrotus,</hi> hauing read <hi>Plato</hi> his booke concerning the immortality of the Soule, was ſo moued therewith, that immediately he caſt downe himſelfe headlong from a loftie turret, thereby thinking to gaine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie. Shall <hi>Platoes</hi> Heathen Philoſophie ſo much preuaile with an Ethnicke, which had no manner feeling of this felicitie, that in hope of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:181123:41"/>immortalitie he bereft himſelfe of life, and ſhall not the moſt ſweet and comfortable promiſes of the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, much more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade vs, which haue the true knowledge of him, and of his Heauenly Kingdome, to forſake theſe vanities, delights and pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>res of the world? Remember often that worthie ſentence: <hi>Hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas:</hi> This life is a moment of time, whereof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of death or life to come dependeth. If it be a moment, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> thereof muſt needs be momentanie, and miſerable is that ioy which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th an end. But the ioyes of Heauen are ſo perfect, that nothing can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> them, nor taken away from them, and therefore perpetuall. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> is the moſt happy and bleſſed place to reſolue, and ſet our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> where no manner of euill ſhall happen vnto vs, nor any plague <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> vs. Therefore ſettle thy ſelfe here, and ſtand faſt againſt all temptation, ſo ſhalt thou more cheerefully ſhake off all carnall burthens, and reereate thy ſelfe in this painefull race and battaile.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philadelph.</speaker>
                  <p>I thanke you for your paines in this conſolatorie motion to caeleſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all glory, wherein you haue much comforted mee with the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of true felicitie. In compariſon whereof, I doe with my heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that all the ioyes of this world are but anguiſh: all mirth, but hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nineſſe: all delight, but ſorrow: all ſweetneſſe, but bitterneſſe: and all the beautie of the fleſh but graſſe, deformitie, and meere vanitie. And thus taking my leaue of you, crauing pardon for my importune holding you, I commend you and my ſelfe to the protection of that great euer-huing God; who keepe vs in true faith, and feare, and ſo prepare vs for death, that we may enioy the Heauenly Felicitie which is to come.</p>
               </sp>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
